<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached in St. Maries Church in Cambridge. By Robert Sheringham, Master of Arts, and Fellow of Gunvil and Caius Colledge.</title>
            <author>Sheringham, Robert, 1602-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E285_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200065</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860869</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E285[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached in St. Maries Church in Cambridge. By Robert Sheringham, Master of Arts, and Fellow of Gunvil and Caius Colledge.</title>
                  <author>Sheringham, Robert, 1602-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iames Young, and are to be sold by John Williams, at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 21st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XLI, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS <hi>PREACHED</hi> IN S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES CHVRCH IN <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY ROBERT SHERINGHAM, Maſter of Arts, and Fellow of GUNVIL and CAIUS Colledge.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iames Young,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Williams,</hi> at the ſigne of the Crowne in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:158509:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158509:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not any excellence that I ſuppoſe to be in mine own labour, hath made me expoſe it to the publique view, but the manifold obligations that I owe to God and the Common-wealth. My deſire is to pay part of a debt, and not to ſet out a <hi>Manifeſto</hi> of mine own merits, which I know how meane and ſmall they are. The firſt and greateſt debt I owe is to God: a debt ſo impoſsible to be fully paid, that whilſt I offer now to pay it but in part, I ſhall make it greater: for all that I can render unto the Lord for all his benefits, is, to endeavour what I can to ſet forth his glory; and when I have done that, I ſhall by ſuch a payment rather encreaſe my debt, then leſſen it, as doing whatſoever I doe by his grace and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistance.
<pb facs="tcp:158509:3"/>Howſoever, I ſhall ſtrive this way to do what I am able; &amp; (when I cannot otherwiſe) labour by encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my debt to pay it. The glory of God is, and I hope ſhall ever be, dearer unto me then my owne life, or hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; were there as many worlds in truth and reality, as ſome Philoſophers have conceited in their fancie, I had rather performe one Act whereby God might bee glorified, then be owner of them all. This that I have now done, I confeſſe, is not much; yet by his own bleſsing, it may in ſome meaſure help to ſet forth his glory: and at the laſt, when the fruit and ſuccceſſe of all mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſhall be made manifest, be a joy and comfort unto me.</p>
            <p>The ſecond debt I owe, is to the Common-wealth; whoſe good, profit, and advantage, all men are bound to promote, according as their reſpective callings and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities ſhall make them capable. For, although our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be various, and ſpring from many ſeverall Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, yet they ought all to meet in the main ſea of <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profit.</hi> They which neglect the common good, and ſeek only occaſions to ſpend their time in eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, are but the ſuperfluities of nature, and may ſeem to be born for no other end but to contradict that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved principle, <hi>that God &amp; nature makes nothing in vain.</hi> The light of the Sunne is ever in action, it produceth gold and ſilver, and rich perfumes, and
<pb facs="tcp:158509:3"/>makes the whole earth pleaſant and fruitfull: the light of knowledge ought to inſpire us alſo with the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivities, he that makes not the light of knowledge as fruitfull in ſpirituall, as that of the Sun is in naturall productions, makes not that gain of knowledge which he ſhould: I will therefore endeavour to make my light active; which, how ſmall and weak ſoever it be, may yet by the gracious aſsiſtance of God, and his concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with it, further the ſpirituall progreſſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſome.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chiefe inducements, which, together with the invitation of divers friends (whereof ſome deſired Copies, determining to put them in print with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge) moved wee to publiſh theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, not intended by me at the firſt to bee made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Many that heard them when they were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, have profeſſed that they were much wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and affected by them: I hope they will have the ſame influence upon thoſe that read them. The faults that are committed in the printing, are neither very many, nor very materiall; yet there are ſome: Some things are ſet down by way of parentheſis, where they ought not: In ſome places divers words are omitted, in others miſtaken. For, by reaſon I could not be preſent to overſee the Preſſe my ſelfe, the Compoſer was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to gueſſe at the words where the Copy was blotted
<pb facs="tcp:158509:4"/>and imperfect, as it was in many places.—Yet theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes have not in any place, that I have obſerved, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depraved the ſenſe, or altered it, although ſometimes they doe a little disfigure the phraſe; and therefore I have not cauſed the <hi>Errata</hi> to be noted at the end. For I deſire not to ſeeme curious, but have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavoured to avoyde curioſitie, eſpecially where I have occaſion to reprehend the faults of any, leſt I ſhould ſeeme to whip them with a poſie. If thou findeſt any thing that proveth uſefull and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto thee, give God the glory, to whoſe protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I will leave thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158509:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM 41.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Heal my ſoul, for I have ſinned againſt thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words were uttered by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in the bitterneſs of his ſoul, after hee had committed the two crying ſins of Adultery and Murther: For <hi>David,</hi> a man after Gods own heart, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">In Pſa. 50.</note> as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks of him, a man that lived as ſtrictly in his kingly palace, as in a cloiſter or monaſtery, fell notwithſtanding into notorious and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous offences: Hee that, like an immoveable rock, had broken the waves of all temptations, was now broken himſelf. In a word; <hi>David,</hi> that victorious King, whom neither the lion, nor the bear, nor <hi>Goliah</hi> himſelfe, the terrour of a whole army, could overcome, was conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158509:5"/>by his owne paſsions, wounded by his own luſt, and brought into that extremity, that neither the balm of Gilead, nor all the phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians there could <hi>heale</hi> thoſe wounds. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſinned, yet he continued not long in his apoſtaſie; as ſoon as the prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to repentance, he confeſſed his fault, &amp; began a repentance that ended not til his death. <hi>There came a traveller</hi> (ſaith the prophet <hi>Nathan</hi>) <hi>unto the rich man, and hee ſpared to take of his owne flock, but took the poor mans lamb, and dreſſed it for the man that was come unto him,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.4. Sinne is there ſtiled but a traveller, for it was none of his domeſtick followers; <hi>Tranſitus erat, non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſio,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De doctr. Chriſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> hee did but lodge ſin for a time, hee did not ſuffer it to dwell with him for ever; for as ſoon as he grew ſenſible of his own diſtemper, he makes his complaint to God, the onely phyſician of his ſoule, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to reſtore and <hi>heal</hi> him. If there be any here then that have imitated <hi>Davids</hi> ſins, learn alſo to imitate his repentance: Sin came to <hi>David</hi> but as a traveller; God grant it comes but as a traveller to you.</p>
            <p>The parts of my Text are three: Firſt, here is <hi>Deſignatio partis vulneratae, Davids</hi> diſcovery
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158509:5"/>of the wounded part, and that was his <hi>ſoule;</hi> Heal my <hi>ſoule.</hi> Secondly, here is <hi>Petitio remedii,</hi> his prayer and petition for a remedy, and that was to be <hi>healed; Heal</hi> my ſoul. Thirdly, here is <hi>Confeſsio cauſae,</hi> his confeſsion of the cauſe of thoſe wounds, and that was his <hi>ſin;</hi> For I have <hi>ſinned</hi> againſt thee. I will begin with the firſt; that is, <hi>Deſignatio partis vulneratae,</hi> his diſcovery of the wounded part.</p>
            <p>The part that was wounded, and that <hi>David</hi> deſired to have healed, was his <hi>ſoul,</hi> the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and moſt excellent part of a man. The <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians</hi> affirme, that ſin can no way wound the <hi>ſoul;</hi> for, being a bare privation, it cannot have, ſay they, a poſitive and naturall act: An errour directly oppoſite to my text.<note place="margin">De natura &amp; gratia, cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid ſanatur, ſi nihil eſt vulneratum, nihil ſauciatum, nihil debilitatum atque vitiatum?</hi> Why doth <hi>David</hi> deſire to have his <hi>ſoule</hi> healed, if nothing in it were wounded, nothing debilitated, nothing corrupted? it is <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> inference out of theſe words. The <hi>Polagians</hi> then were full of vain preſumption, or elſe <hi>David</hi> was full of vain fears: But <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> fears were juſt, and he ſpake theſe words out of experience and a deep ſenſe of his own miſeries. For, if wee deſcend into particulars,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158509:6"/>wee ſhall ſee his <hi>ſoule</hi> had many wounds; it had ſome as old as it ſelfe, his <hi>ſoule</hi> was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as ſoon as it was created; God gave him life, and ſin death, at the ſame inſtant: for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> together with all mankind, ſinned in our firſt parents, and was wounded in his <hi>ſoule</hi> by that originall ſinne which hee derived from them: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>I was ſhapen in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in ſin did my mother conceive mee, Pſal.</hi> 51.5. Here was a ſin, and therefore a wound at his firſt conception.<note place="margin">Apol. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> Contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianum l. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls it <hi>naturale contagium,</hi> a naturall contagion. S. <hi>Auguſtine, morbum &amp; languorem naturae,</hi> the diſeaſe and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of nature: And this wound was deep enough, had he had no other; for origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſin hath not onely wounded the <hi>ſoule,</hi> but it hath wounded all her powers and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it hath wounded the <hi>affections;</hi> for whileſt man ſtood in the integrity of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all his <hi>affections</hi> were regulated and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by reaſon: the ſuperiour faculties of the <hi>ſoule</hi> exerciſed a kind of regall authority and juriſdiction over the inferiour, and the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did inviolably performe thoſe duties that were required of them: Man was like a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158509:6"/>Common-wealth, like <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that was <hi>built as a city that is at unity with it ſelfe:</hi> but ſin hath now ſo wounded the <hi>affections,</hi> that they are no longer enclined, or naturally able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the decrees of reaſon; but as a ſhip is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up and downe by the violence of the waves in a tempeſt at ſea, ſo a man is carried by the violence of his owne <hi>affections:</hi> hee is driven by them, as by ſtrong and impetuous windes, upon many rocks. Now the inferiour faculties of the <hi>ſoule</hi> reſiſt the ſuperiour, the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> (like ſeditious Tribunes) being alwayes ready to ſtir up commotions: <hi>I ſee another law in my members</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>warring againſt the law of my mind, Rom.</hi> 7.23. The <hi>affections</hi> are at warre with reaſon, and force it oftentimes to ſtoop to their unreaſonable and unjuſt commands. This is the firſt wound of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> which is called <hi>imbecilitas &amp; naturalis infirmitas,</hi> imbecility and naturall infirmity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It hath wounded the <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> for the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> did naturally appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend truth without difficulty; and as the eye looketh upon a beautifull object, ſo the <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> looked upon truth with delight and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158509:7"/>pleaſure; and the more excellent and eminent the truths were, the greater pleaſure had the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> in the contemplation of them: It was not ſubject to be deluded by the falſe inſinuations of any affection, but could upon deliberation clearly diſcern all naturall truths; and as for thoſe truths that were ſupernaturall and above its capacity, as many of them as were neceſſary to be known, were infuſed, or revealed by God when he firſt created it: But ſin hath likewiſe ſo wounded the <hi>vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> as it can hardly apprehend its firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples without difficulty. Now reaſon, like <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> takes part with rebellious <hi>Abſolom,</hi> the corrupt affections; and is apt to repreſent things to the will, not as they are in themſelves, but as the affections pleaſe. Now the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> is filled with ignorance and obſcurity, and hath loſt that knowledge that was revealed to our firſt parents, and which ſhould likewiſe have beene revealed to all their poſterity, together with the light whereby it was able to judge and diſcern ſupernaturall truths. So that there is a double ignorance in the <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from a double defect and want in the <hi>ſoul.</hi> The firſt kind of ignorance ariſeth from want
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158509:7"/>of ſufficient revelation; for, naturally, the <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> cannot know the articles of faith. God hath given to every thing a certain circuit, and determinate ſphere of activity beyond which it cannot paſſe; as fire can heate to a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate diſtance, but cannot paſſe beyond that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: The <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> hath a ſphere of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity too, it hath a naturall ſufficiency to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſome truths, ſuch as are of the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſuch as it can come unto by the knowledge of the ſenſes; but cannot paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them to thoſe that are ſupernaturall. The ſecond kind of ignorance ariſeth from want of evidence after ſufficient revelation, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes joyned with falſhood, or doubt: Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ariſeth from deception, when the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> apprehends errour for truth in things ſpeculative; or in things practicall, when it apprehends that goodneſſe to be in ſome acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which is not; and in others, that goodneſſe to be wanting which is in them. Doubt ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from irreſolution: I ſpeak not now of irreſolution in matters of action, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long properly to the will; but of irreſolution in matters of judgement, which belong to the <hi>vnderſtanding:</hi> for, there is an irreſolution in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158509:8"/>the will, and an irreſolution in the <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;</hi> as a Judge ſometimes knowes the law, and yet ſuſpends judgement out of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality and affection; and this is called <hi>ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio facti,</hi> a ſuſpenſion of fact: and ſometimes when reaſons are equall on both ſides, hee knowes not to whom the lawes incline, and ſo ſuſpends judgement for want of evidence; and this is called <hi>ſuſpenſio juris,</hi> a ſuſpenſion of right. So it is likewiſe in the <hi>ſoul;</hi> ſometimes a man knows what hee ought to doe, but yet, out of particular and private reſpects, reſolves upon nothing; here the ſuſpenſe is in the will, and is anſwerable to that which in a Judge is called <hi>ſuſpenſio facti:</hi> and ſometimes, when ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are equall on both ſides, hee knowes not what to reſolve upon for want of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; here the ſuſpence is in the <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and is anſwerable to that which in a Judge is called <hi>ſuſpenſio juris:</hi> In the firſt caſe there is a conflict of ſeverall deſires; in the laſt, a conflict of ſeverall thoughts. And from this kind of irreſolution proceed all doubts and ſcruples in matters of conſcience, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be not joyned with falſhood, becauſe the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> hath made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158509:8"/>yet they are alwayes joyned with ignorance. And this is the ſecond wound of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> which is called <hi>Ignorantia &amp; coecitas mentis,</hi> ignorance and blindneſſe of mind.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It hath wounded the <hi>will,</hi> that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme facultie of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> and miſtreſſe of all the other; for the <hi>will</hi> was once able to rule the affections, and to hold them all in ſubjection: it had a naturall power to love God, and a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination carrying all her deſires to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: But ſin hath now wounded the <hi>will</hi> alſo, and deprived it of thoſe naturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections wherewith it was created; it is now inclined to love the creatures, and to deſire and long after them more then after God. Could wee but penetrate with our bodily eyes into the <hi>ſouls</hi> of men, and behold all the ſeverall acts of their <hi>wills,</hi> wee ſhould ſee an admirable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and multitude of deſires, but all fixt upon the creatures; wee ſhould ſee ſome deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring riches, others honour, others to ſpend their dayes in luſt and pleaſure; we ſhould ſee ſome tranſported with love, others with jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie; wee ſhould ſee an infinite number of deſires, but all pointed downwards towards tranſitory and earthly things. How few are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158509:9"/>there whoſe deſires fly upward? Who is there that will ſay, I deſire to enjoy God, though it coſt me my luſt, my riches, mine honour, and all that I poſſeſſe? The name of happineſſe is pleaſing to our ears, but wee regard not the thing it ſelfe, or at leaſt we purſue the ſhadow whileſt the ſubſtance flies from us; our diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered paſsions do now ſo over-rule our <hi>wills,</hi> that wee preferre lies before truth, vice before vertue, the vain delights of the body before the true and ſolid contentments of the mind; wee preferre the ſpurious pleaſures of our ſenſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe which are legitimate, which vertue receives and approves: Whileſt wee ſhould moderate our affections, and eſtabliſh a dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and laſting peace within our ſelves, we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give way to their diſorders, and ſuffer our happineſſe to be interrupted by their exceſſe and riot. Our <hi>wils</hi> are full of inordinate and unſatiable deſires, and are become ſoft and plyable to evill, but hard and impenetrable to every good motion. This is the third wound of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> which is called <hi>Malitia &amp; duritas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> malice and hardneſſe of heart.</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all; Sin hath made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wound in the <hi>ſoule,</hi> which troubles it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158509:9"/>worſe then all the reſt, and that is in the <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> In the ſpirituall conflict between ſin and the <hi>ſoul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22.34.</note> the <hi>conſcience</hi> may ſay like <hi>Ahab, Take mee out of the battell, for I am wounded.</hi> There are two effects of ſin, <hi>macula,</hi> &amp; <hi>reatus,</hi> the <hi>ſtain</hi> of ſin, and the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin; the <hi>ſtain</hi> of ſin is that diſtemper and vitious inclination that ſin leaveth behind it, and this adheres to the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties before mentioned: The <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin is the obligation to puniſhment that lies upon every ſinner after hee hath committed it: for as hee that breaks the provinciall laws and cuſtomes of any common-wealth, is guilty of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which the ſanction and penalty of the law provides in that common-wealth; ſo he that ſins againſt God, is guilty of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment appointed by his law: and this guilt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to the <hi>conſcience.</hi> Thus ſin hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the powers and faculties of the <hi>ſoul;</hi> not by any poſitive acts, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> ſuppoſed a neceſsity; but by depriving it of that originall juſtice wherewith it was created: as a man may overthrow a building as well by taking away a pillar, as by applying outward force. The want of originall juſtice hath made the <hi>ſoul</hi> lame and imperfect: hee that hath one leg
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158509:10"/>ſhorter then another, cannot chuſe but halt, and goe unequally in his naturall motion; and the <hi>ſoul</hi> that is moved by Reaſon &amp; Affections, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam à duobus pedibus inaequalibus,</hi> as by two un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall legs, cannot chuſe but halt and goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally in its morall motion: for whileſt it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the motion of its longer leg, Reaſon, it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth towards heaven; but whilſt it follows the motion of its ſhorter leg, the Affections, it falleth towards the earth: God, to ſupply this ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality and defect, created the <hi>ſoul</hi> with origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall juſtice, which did after a manner ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the Affections, and kept the whole <hi>ſoul</hi> in ſuch a frame and temper, that all her faculties moved towards heaven. But man ſinned, and God, as a juſt judgement, took from him that originall juſtice that upheld his nature, for want whereof the <hi>ſoul</hi> is fallen into that decay, and become ſubject to thoſe vvounds and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that I have named. This is every finners condition, and this was <hi>Davids</hi> condition, hee was wounded in all the powers and faculties of his <hi>ſoul;</hi> he was wounded in his <hi>affections,</hi> in his <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> in his <hi>will,</hi> and in his <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and all theſe wounds were the effects of originall ſin.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:158509:10"/>
            <p>But <hi>David</hi> had yet more vvounds, <hi>David</hi> had his perſonall and actuall ſins; which, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did not wound new faculties (for originall ſin had vvounded all before;) yet they made new vvounds: but if I ſhould undertake to ſhew you all thoſe wounds, I ſhould undertake that which himſelf was not able to performe, though more privie to his owne actions:<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>Who can tell</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>how oft hee offendeth?</hi> His words have the forme of a queſtion, but the force of a peremptory aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as the Philoſopher ſpeaks) queſtions which have the force of affirmative or negative propoſitions, and ſo hath this here: <hi>Davids Quis intelligit?</hi> is as much as <hi>Nullus intelligit;</hi> and if no man can number his ſins, then ſurely no man can number the vvounds of his <hi>ſoule,</hi> for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinne is as deadly as the firſt, it vvounds as deep, though it vvounds not ſo many; and theſe wounds vvere dangerous, though but light in compariſon of others: for <hi>David</hi> had ſins of preſumption alſo, ſins againſt his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and againſt his conſcience; but thoſe ſins vvhich made the vvorſt vvounds, and which he deſires in my Text eſpecially to have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158509:11"/>healed, were his adultery, and his murther. In the next Pſalm to my Text he complains of the bitterneſſe of thoſe wounds; <hi>Why art thou ſo full of heavineſſe, O my ſoul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.11.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>and why art thou ſo diſquieted within mee?</hi> here was heavineſſe and diſquietneſſe in his <hi>ſoul,</hi> and all this the effect of thoſe wounds: His adultery and murther were ſins of an high nature, and moſt of all deſtructive to the <hi>ſoule: Whoſo committeth adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with a woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>lacketh under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; hee that doth it deſtroyeth his owne ſoul, Prov.</hi> 6.31. Adultery (you ſee) deſtroyes the <hi>ſoul,</hi> it wounds it mortally: and murther is no leſſe deſtructive then adultery; <hi>Yee know</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John</hi>) <hi>that no murtherer hath eternall life abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.15. This ſin doth not onely deprive the <hi>ſoul</hi> of health, but of life it ſelfe, it kils the <hi>ſoul</hi> outright: this made <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, <hi>My wickedneſſes are gone over mine head, and are like a ſore burden too heavie for mee to bear, Pſal.</hi> 38.4. The cruell and unnaturall homicide ſheds his brothers bloud, and it falls upon the earth, and the earth ſeems to drink it up; and yet the word of God ſaith, that it reſt upon the head of the murtherer, and ſo it reſted upon <hi>Davids</hi> head: that bloud that ranne in <hi>Uriah's</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:158509:11"/>veins to preſerve his life, ſits now heavie upon <hi>Davids</hi> head to procure his death; it was time for <hi>David</hi> to have his <hi>ſoul</hi> healed, it having ſo many deep and deadly wounds: And yet hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was ſcarce ſufficient; for, in another Pſalm, hee ſeems to require more; <hi>Create in me a clean heart, O God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and renew a right ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, Pſal.</hi> 51.10. All the faculties of his <hi>ſoul</hi> were ſo wounded by thoſe ſins, that he deſireth not there a reparation, but a new creation. And theſe ſins conſidered <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> ſimply and by themſelves, did deeply wound his <hi>ſoul;</hi> but if we conſider them in <hi>concreto,</hi> with all their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts, we may find many circumſtances that made his wounds the greater; for <hi>David</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both a King and a Prophet; and, as a Prophet, was bound to inſtruct; as a King, to protect the lives and chaſtity of his ſubjects. For <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> ſomething may be ſaid in her excuſe, for it was hard for her to reſiſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of a King: but all circumſtances ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate <hi>Davids</hi> ſin; his holy profeſsion, and the ſword of juſtice which God had put into his hand to puniſh ſuch offences, ought to have reſtrained himſelfe from committing them. This ſin in <hi>David</hi> did not onely wound his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158509:12"/>owne <hi>ſoul,</hi> but it wounded the whole Church, and laid it open to the calumnies and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the heathen: for, as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> witneſſeth, In the primitive times of the Church, when the contention was hot between the Chriſtians and the heathen concerning the truth of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the heathen objected this againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; <hi>Ecce quomodo Chriſtiani innocentiam ſequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoleg. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fidem praeferunt, religionem venerantur, caſtita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem docent, quorum principes homicidia &amp; adulteria feciſſe produntur:</hi> Behold (ſaid they) how the Chriſtians imbrace innocence, extoll faith, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour religion, teach chaſtity, whoſe chiefeſt maſters were both murtherers and adulterers. But I will inſiſt no longer upon theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, neither will I ſpeak of his other ſins ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant to theſe; of his making <hi>Uriah</hi> drunk, to conceal and palliate his adultery; of his ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, in rewarding <hi>Uriah</hi> with death, whoſe faithfull ſervices ought to have been rewarded with honour; of his deep hypocriſie, in being preſent at the ſervice of God, and offering ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the ſpace of nine moneths together, polluted in the mean time with theſe horrible crimes: theſe and the reſt I will paſſe over, leſt, as <hi>Shimei</hi> reviled him in his life, ſo I may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158509:12"/>ſeem to revile him after death. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath made an apologie in his defence; and, for my part, I will not make an invective a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: God himſelf hath juſtified him, and then who ſhall condemn him? I have only na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his principall ſins, that (according as my Text requires) I might ſhew you the <hi>wounds</hi> of his <hi>ſoul:</hi> Now therefore I will leave him, and come to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And firſt, ſince ſin doth wound the <hi>ſoul,</hi> let us be carefull and watchfull over it; for the <hi>ſoul</hi> is the moſt noble and excellent part of a man. A man conſiſts of two parts, a <hi>body,</hi> and a <hi>ſoul;</hi> and both theſe have their naturall beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and excellency: The excellency of the <hi>body</hi> (if wee conſider the outward forme and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip) is very wonderfull; <hi>I will praiſe thee,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>for I am fearfully and wonderfully made, Pſal.</hi> 139.14. He uſeth two termes here to expreſſe the rarity of this work, <hi>fearfully,</hi> and <hi>wonderfully;</hi> as if the ſtructure of mans <hi>body</hi> were ſo artificially framed, that the ſight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was not onely able to beget fear, but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and aſtoniſhment. And in the next verſe he adds further; <hi>I am curiouſly wrought in the lowest parts of the earth:</hi> the Originall hath it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158509:13"/>that is, <hi>I am curiouſly imbroydered;</hi> as if mans <hi>body</hi> were made like a piece of Phrygian work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, being variouſly wrought with veins, and ſinewes, and bones, and muſcles: ſo that wee have reaſon to be carefull of our <hi>bodies,</hi> and if they be wounded at any time, to make proviſion for their health. How much more then ought we to be carefull of our <hi>ſouls,</hi> whoſe excellency, like <hi>Benjamins</hi> meſſe, is five times as much as the excellency of the <hi>body?</hi> The <hi>ſoul</hi> of man is a divine ſubſtance, a rich and noble poſſeſsion, the greateſt gift and moſt precious that a man ever received from the liberall hand of his Creatour; it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Gregory Nyſſen:</hi> by it wee know the height, the breadth, and depth of the heavens, the number of the ſtars, their greatneſſe, diſtances, &amp; approaches. What ſhould I ſpeak of Divinity, Philoſophy, the Mathematicks? What ſhould I ſpeak of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; Poeſie, of all the Sciences and Arts, as well liberall, as mechanicall, the knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee attain unto by the benefit of the <hi>ſoul?</hi> By it, a man being but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſtiles him) a ſhort creature, not above a yard and an halfe long, obtaines the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158509:13"/>government of the whole world: By it, the Patriarchs, Prophets, and Apoſtles ſpake unto God, received divine revelations, learned many ſecret and ineffable myſteries, and knew upon earth what things were done in heaven. Hee that knoweth not the worth of this jewell, may undervalue it; but a skilfull Jeweller that knowes the properties and excellencie of it, will prize it above the whole world. Such a Jeweller is God; who, for the deſire he had to thoſe jewels, aſſumed our humane nature; and when he could not have them at a cheaper rate, hee tooke them in exchange for his own bloud. Such Jewelers are the Angels, which watch continually over mens <hi>ſouls,</hi> that they may keep and preſerve theſe jewels deputed to their cuſtody. And ſuch a Jeweller (if I may lawfully rank him in this place) is the Divell, who, to get theſe jewels, goes about continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and compaſſeth the whole earth. Seeing the <hi>ſoule</hi> then is of ſo great excellencie, let us be carefull and watchfull over it; let us not ſuffer ſuch a divine, learned, noble and active creature to periſh by our negligence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Seeing ſin doth wound the <hi>ſoul,</hi> let it be our chiefeſt care to avoid ſin; let
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:158509:14"/>us not ſet our affections upon it, but flye from it as from a deadly enemy. The world ſets too high a price upon her owne beauty; for her faireſt things are but imperfect and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive: her wiſdome is but fooliſhneſſe, her light but darkneſſe, her riches but poverty: What ſhall wee ſay then of her deformities? her pride, ambition, luſt, and all her other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which men falſly think pleaſures, but are indeed the price of their <hi>ſouls</hi>) are ſo far from being good, as they are the worſt of evils: for, how can wee reckon thoſe among the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of good things, which deſtroy the <hi>ſoul?</hi> God is the life of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> let us ſet our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon him: Why ſhould wee turn from God, who is the ſubſtance, and run after crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are but images and imperfect ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umbrations of his beauty? Why ſhould wee embrace the ſhadow, and let the ſubſtance go? It hath pleaſed God to condeſcend ſo much as to love the <hi>ſoul,</hi> and to contract it to himſelfe in a ſacred and ſpirituall marriage: the <hi>ſoul</hi> is Gods wife; and God, like an indulgent and loving husband, hath given her all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be her ſervants: but the <hi>ſoul</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſets her affections upon the creatures, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158509:14"/>
               <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife ſet her affections upon her ſervant <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and the creatures,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.7.</note> as if they were ſenſible of the injury which the <hi>ſoul</hi> offers to God, fly from the <hi>ſoul,</hi> as <hi>Joſeph</hi> fled from his miſtreſſe: ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and honours, and worldly delights do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes fly from the <hi>ſoul</hi> that purſues them, as if they were unwilling to be the cauſes of her adultery: Let us not then fly after our owne deſtruction, or ſet our affections upon thoſe things whoſe love brings death, not health to the <hi>ſoul.</hi> In heaven there are none of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights which worldly men uſe moſt to admire, and for which they are wont moſt to hazzard their <hi>ſouls;</hi> and yet there is perfect and true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Can wee not then want thoſe things here for a little while, and not think our ſelves miſerable, which in heaven wee ſhall want for ever, and yet be moſt perfectly and truely happy? Mee thinks wee ſhould rather ſet our affections upon God, who is the bridegroom of our <hi>ſouls,</hi> and who loves us in that exceſſe, that it is impoſsible wee ſhould return him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall love: yet, though wee cannot love him equally, let us love him again with the beſt affection that we can; and, as it did not grieve us to leave the delights of children after wee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:158509:15"/>became men; ſo, let it not grieve us to leave the delights of worldly men after wee be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to this ſacred and holy union with God. And ſo much of the firſt part of my Text, which is <hi>Deſignatio partis vulneratae; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> diſcovery of the wounded part. I come now to the ſecond, that is, <hi>Petitio remedii,</hi> his prayer and petition for a remedy:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heal</hi> my ſoule. I have ſhowne you already that <hi>David</hi> was wounded in all the faculties of his ſoul; and therefore this petition muſt be applyed to all: and firſt, to the <hi>affections; Heal</hi> my <hi>affections:</hi> For, except the <hi>affections</hi> be <hi>healed,</hi> their diſtempers work upon the whole ſoul. A wound in any one part of the body infects the whole; if one member ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, all the members ſuffer with it; not onely becauſe of the ſympathy which one part hath with another, but becauſe the bloud, paſsing through the infected place, carrieth with it ſome of the corrupt humors: ſo it is likewiſe in the ſoule, if one faculty ſuffers, all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſuffer with it, not onely by reaſon of the ſympathy which one faculty hath with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but becauſe there is a mutuall influence between them, by transfuſion of their quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158509:15"/>into one another; for, Reaſon is corrupted by the <hi>affections,</hi> as bloud is corrupted by an ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerous part of the body, and infects both the Underſtanding and the Will by their contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>David</hi> found this by experience; for the ſenſitive part made the rationall to tranſgreſſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi> The firſt hurt which hee received was at the eye, and from thence it was derived to the heart; his <hi>affections</hi> corrupted his <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> and his <hi>will,</hi> and therefore his <hi>affections</hi> muſt firſt be <hi>healed. Heal</hi> my ſoul, that is, change my <hi>affections;</hi> for the ſoul cannot be <hi>healed</hi> till the <hi>affections</hi> be changed. There is an outward <hi>healing,</hi> and there is an inward <hi>healing;</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>healing</hi> cauſeth a true and reall change in the <hi>affections,</hi> the outward <hi>healing</hi> cauſeth a change only in outward appearance, and doth not properly <hi>heal</hi> the wound, but cover it: for, after this outward <hi>healing,</hi> the wound is ſtill as great, and the danger greater; as a wound which is <hi>healed</hi> in the outward skin and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the body, if it bleed inwardly, is ſo much the more dangerous, by how much it is more inward and unſuſpected. Now this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>healing</hi> is wrought divers wayes:</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:158509:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:158509:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:158509:17"/>
            <p>Firſt, by <hi>time:</hi> In old age divers <hi>affections</hi> ſeem to be <hi>healed,</hi> the flame of luſt ſeems to be extinguiſhed; and yet in many it is not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, though it burne leſſe violently, or ſeems not to burn at all. <hi>Tutò tractatur ſerpens dum riget frigore; non deeſt illi venenum, ſed torpet:</hi> a ſerpent cannot ſting whileſt his members are numb with cold, and yet hee wants not poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſtrength to ſhoot it forth: and there are many, becauſe of the coldneſſe proper to old age, want ſtrength to execute, but not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>affections</hi> to move them to all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; had they ſufficient heat to cheriſh their corrupt <hi>affections,</hi> they are not ſo <hi>healed,</hi> but that they would ſoon break into their former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies and exceſſe of luſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by <hi>place:</hi> Hee that lives in a cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or call, where the <hi>affections</hi> want outward objects to vvork upon them, may think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>healed,</hi> and the vvorld may think him a new man; and yet his <hi>affections</hi> may be ſtill the ſame. That fire vvhich is buryed in aſhes, ſhevves not the ſame fury vvhich another fire doth, that meets vvith fit matter to kindle it; not becauſe it hath loſt its naturall property, but becauſe it vvants like nouriſhment: and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158509:17"/>many that live in retirement, ſequeſtred from all worldly affairs, abſtain from many wrongs and inſolencies that other men commit; not becauſe their <hi>affections</hi> are leſſe furiouſly encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to doe wrong, but becauſe they want the ſame outward matter to incenſe and kindle them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the <hi>perſons</hi> among whom we live: They that live in a well-ordered Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, where the care and vigilance of the Magiſtrate ſuppreſſeth all vice; or they that converſe daily with good men; may, in the former caſe for fear, in the later, for ſhame, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all notorious and infamous ſins; and may ſeem (both to themſelves and others) to be juſt, patient, chaſte, and temperate; and yet not have their <hi>affections healed.</hi> As ſtones that lie in the top of an high tower have not loſt their weight and naturall inclination to deſcend downeward, but are ſuſtained by the other parts of the building: ſo there are ſome ſupported by others, not by the ſoundneſſe of their own <hi>affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this outward <hi>healing</hi> is not here meant: <hi>David</hi> deſired to have his <hi>affections</hi> changed and <hi>healed</hi> inwardly; which neither <hi>time,</hi> nor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158509:18"/>
               <hi>place,</hi> nor the <hi>perſons</hi> that were about him could effect: it is onely grace can <hi>heal</hi> the <hi>affections</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; and ſo grace is here the ſubject matter of his petition; for the wounds of ſin are too deep to be <hi>healed</hi> by any means leſſe powerfull then grace: And if man in his innocency, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſupernaturall gifts, continued not long in the purity of his nature; how much leſſe ſhall wounded nature, without ſupernaturall gifts, recover her former purity? Yet I deny not, but that a man may, by the help of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, obtain habits that may have an inward operation upon the ſoule, and may change the <hi>affections</hi> in ſome degree; but in a degree ſo weak and imperfect as can never bring him to ſalvation. A man may by the ſtrength of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, aſsiſted only by the generall ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, acquire habits of vertue, and thoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits may cauſe a readineſſe in the <hi>affections</hi> to turn to vertuous actions: yet thoſe acts of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue will differ much from thoſe that ſpring from grace. Actions that ſpring from nature, if they be done out of a love to honeſty, and be without the mixture of all private reſpects, may have a morall goodneſſe; and I think they may truely be called vertues: yet actions that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158509:18"/>ſpring from grace will as far excell them, as domeſtick fruits that are kept and fomented by an husbandman, excell thoſe that grow naturally in the woods and open fields: for grace changes the <hi>affections</hi> more powerfully, and ſo makes the work, which is partly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the <hi>affections,</hi> to be of greater value. Our Saviour Chriſt, having examined this matter by his infallible ſcrutiny, aſcribes more worth to a ſmall gift which a poor widow brought into the treaſurie, then to the large gifts of many rich men; <hi>Of a truth</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I ſay unto you, that this poor widow hath caſt in more then they all, Luk.</hi> 21.3. They from their great heaps brought great gifts, ſhee from a ſmall heap brought onely two mites; and yet our Saviour Chriſt, having weighed all their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt hers, found, that many graines would not make them equall: for, though their gifts were voluntary as well as hers, yet they were not ſo much voluntary, becauſe their <hi>affections</hi> were not ſo ready; for the <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> work upon the Will: when the <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are not ready, <hi>retardunt, ſi non impediunt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem,</hi> they hinder and ſtop the Will, if they doe not divert her from a right courſe. There
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158509:19"/>being then great difference between nature and grace in working upon the <hi>affections,</hi> their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects muſt needs be different: Nature may cauſe ſome change in the <hi>affections,</hi> and perfect them in ſome degree; but grace changes the <hi>affections</hi> powerfully, and makes them as it were new <hi>affections: If any man be in Chriſt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>hee is a new creature; old things are paſſed away, behold all things are become new,</hi> 2 <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            <p>And yet grace doth not totally <hi>heal</hi> the <hi>affections</hi> in this world: there is but a partiall <hi>healing</hi> here, <hi>the fleſh luſteth against the ſpirit</hi> in the beſt men; luſtfull, ambitious, covetous, and an innumerable company of unlawfull thoughts and deſires will ſometimes ariſe in every man: they which have obtained the greateſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace, had never ſufficient to exſiccate and dry up the ſtreames of thoſe impurities; yet this is our comfort, thoſe wounds that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine are not left for our deſtruction, but our tryall; the danger and deadlineſſe of them is taken away, although they be not perfectly <hi>healed.</hi> As God left the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and the <hi>Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,</hi> and the <hi>Ammonites</hi> amongſt the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not to conſume his people, but to prove
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158509:19"/>them; ſo hee leaves ſeverall kinds of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence in his children, not to deſtroy us, but to try whether wee will abſtain from ſin for his ſake, when our <hi>affections</hi> move us to the contrary: and as <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 10.18.</note> having overcome the five Kings that combined againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> did not preſently put them to death, but kept them in a cave, that hee might put them to death afterwards in the ſight of all the people with greater triumph; ſo God, having by his grace ſubdued the concupiſcence and inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateneſſe of the <hi>affections,</hi> doth not preſently deſtroy them, but keeps them a while in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, deprived of their wonted liberty, that he may deſtroy them afterwards in the ſight of all the world with greater glory. At the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall judgement, <hi>when this corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, and this mortall ſhall put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi> all inordinateneſſe ſhall be deſtroyed, the <hi>affections</hi> ſhall be totally <hi>healed;</hi> then the ſoule, like the ſick man in the Goſpel, ſhall <hi>take up his bed and walk;</hi> it ſhall take the body, wherein it lay ſick as in a bed, and carry it where it pleaſe; <hi>portabit lectum à quo ante por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus fuerat,</hi> it ſhall carry that whereby it ſelfe was carried; then the fleſh ſhall yeeld to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158509:20"/>ſpirit, and ſhall rejoyce to be overcome. In the mean time, the concupiſcence and inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our <hi>affections</hi> are ſo <hi>healed,</hi> that they ceaſe to reigne, though they ceaſe not to be; we may by the help of grace ſubdue our <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> though wee cannot keep them from rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. And this is the firſt thing to which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids petition</hi> muſt be applyed; namely, to the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the next place, this petition muſt be applied to the <hi>vnderſtanding, Heal</hi> my <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:</hi> for the wound of Ignorance is as great as the wound of Infirmity, and therefore that muſt be <hi>healed</hi> too, or elſe the ſoul will be never the better. And here two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; for, as I ſhewed you before, there is a double Ignorance in the <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> ariſing from a double defect and want in the ſoule; the firſt ariſeth for want of ſufficient <hi>revelation,</hi> the ſoul having loſt the knowledge of thoſe truths that were revealed by God to our firſt parents. The ſecond ariſeth for want of <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> after ſufficient <hi>revelation,</hi> the <hi>vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> being not able of it ſelfe to aſſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed truths without ſome light given her by God, whereby it may diſcover the certainty of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158509:20"/>them. And therefore two things are required, I ſay, to <hi>heale</hi> theſe two kindes of Ignorance; The firſt is <hi>divine revelation.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine illumination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing neceſſary to <hi>heal</hi> the wound of Ignorance is <hi>divine revelation:</hi> The articles of faith muſt be revealed immediately by God himſelfe, as they were to the Patriarchs and the Apoſtles; or mediately by the working and adminiſtration of the Church, or elſe they can never be known; <hi>Thou art bleſſed,</hi> Simon Barjona, (ſaith our Saviour Chriſt unto Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>for fleſh and bloud bath not revealed this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, but my Father which is in heaven, Matth.</hi> 16.16. The revelations of fleſh and bloud doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inlarge, then <hi>heal</hi> the wound of Ignorance. Whileſt <hi>Solomon</hi> followed the revelations of fleſh and bloud, hee loſt that knowledge that was before revealed; and as formerly for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, ſo afterward for ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie and fooliſhneſſe, hee became a ſecond time the wonder and amazement of the world. The myſteries of faith muſt be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from above, or they can never be revealed; <hi>No man knoweth the Son</hi> (ſaith our Saviour Chriſt) <hi>but the Father; neither knoweth any man the Father,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:158509:21"/>but the Son, and hee to whom the Son will reveale him, Matth.</hi> 11.27.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing neceſſary to <hi>heale</hi> the wound of Ignorance is <hi>divine illumination:</hi> for, after the articles of faith be revealed, if there be not ſomething elſe added to make the truth evident, the <hi>vnderstanding</hi> will either be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by falſhood, or elſe perplexed by doubts and ſcruples. The eye cannot diſcern an object, though preſent, except there be light to make it viſible: and although the articles of faith be ſufficiently preſented to the <hi>vnderstanding</hi> by ſupernaturall revelation; yet if there be not a ſupernaturall light too, to make the truth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the wound of Ignorance cannot be <hi>healed.</hi> Naturall Reaſon is too weak to enlighten the ſoule ſufficiently: for, as <hi>Noah's</hi> dove could find no reſt in the air for the ſole of her foot; ſo when the <hi>vnderstanding</hi> enters into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of ſupernaturall truths, as in the thin and ſubtile air, it can find nothing to reſt on: or, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had ſunk when hee walked upon the ſea,<note place="margin">Matth. 14.30, 31.</note> if our Saviour Chriſt had not upholden him with his hands; ſo the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> ſinks when it walks upon the deep ocean of ſupernaturall truths, if it be not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:158509:21"/>by divine aſsiſtance. And yet, as Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may move the affections in order to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall goodneſſe, but cannot <hi>heal</hi> their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity; ſo it can likewiſe enlighten the <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> in order to ſupernaturall truths, but cannot <hi>heal</hi> its ignorance. The light of Reaſon may make ſupernaturall truths ſo evident to the <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> that a man may think his faith perfect in all reſpects; and yet it may be perfect in nothing. The ancient Fathers of the Church, in their Apologies for Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, alledge many reaſons which may make a naturall man beleeve the articles of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith. The miracles which were wrought by the Apoſtles have given their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſuch authority, that a naturall man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but aſſent unto it, unleſſe his <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> be carried away by ſome private reſpect and intereſt of his own: And hee that hath this aſſent may think his <hi>underſtanding</hi> is enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and <hi>healed</hi> ſufficiently; but hee deceives himſelf, like the <hi>Syrians,</hi> which thought they had been in the way to the Prophet,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.20.</note> when they were in the midſt of Samaria; or like <hi>Sauls</hi> meſſengers,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 19.16.</note> which thought they had found <hi>David,</hi> when they found but an image
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:158509:22"/>in his place: For this faith that ſprings from naturall Reaſon is but <hi>imago &amp; ſimulacrum fidei,</hi> the image and repreſentation of true faith; it is like it in ſhew, but differeth much from it in eſſence. For there are two properties eſſentiall to true faith, which nothing but the light of grace can work in the ſoul. The firſt is <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty:</hi> Nothing but the light of grace can work in us ſuch a <hi>certainty</hi> as is eſſentiall to true faith. Hee that beleeves a thing certainly, muſt have ſome infallible motive, <hi>cui falſum ſubeſſe non poteſt,</hi> in which there can be no er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or deluſion; for an uncertaine motive can give a man no aſſurance of that which he beleeves: <hi>Certainty</hi> of faith alwayes ſuppoſeth a certain and infallible motive upon which it is built. Now concerning the articles of our faith, nothing but the light of grace can give us an infallible motive of their truth; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them being above Reaſon, cannot by the light of Reaſon be made evident.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps will ſay, A naturall man, by the light of Reaſon, may beleeve the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to be true, and to be the word of God, and ſo may have an infallible motive: For hee that beleeves the articles of faith becauſe they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:158509:22"/>are grounded upon the authority of Gods word, hath a ſure and certain motive of their truth, it being impoſsible that any falſhood ſhould proceed from God.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: Although a naturall man may beleeve the Scriptures to be true, and to be the word of God, yet his faith concerning this matter is but an hiſtoricall kind of faith, and is grounded upon deceitfull and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain motives: and therefore though the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures be an infallible motive to thoſe that have certaine grounds to beleeve them to be true, and to be the word of God; yet they can be no infallible motive to him that hath not ſuch grounds: for they that are not ſure that the Scriptures are true, and that they are the word of God, cannot be ſure that any thing is true which they prove from them. Now a naturall man cannot, from the light of Reaſon, have any other but uncertain and deceitfull grounds concerning the truth of Scripture; for hee beleeves them to be true, and to be the word of God, either from the tradition of the Church, from the miracles which were wrought by the Apoſtles, or from ſome other humane motive; in which, although there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:158509:23"/>be great probability, yet there can be no infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. Such grounds as theſe can give him no ſuch aſſurance as excludes all poſsibility of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; he hath but an hiſtoricall faith of the truth of Scripture, and ſo can have but an hiſtoricall <hi>certainty.</hi> But the light of grace ſhewes us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly the truth of Scripture, it gives us an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall knowledge of it, and makes us as it were to ſee it with our eyes: ſo that there is as great a difference between the faith that a man hath from the light of Reaſon, and that which hee hath afterward from the light of grace, as there was between the faith which the Samaritans had of our Saviour Chriſt from the ſpeech of the woman, and that which they had afterwards when they ſaw him with their eyes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond property eſſentiall to true faith, which nothing but the light of grace can work in the ſoul, is a <hi>pious affection</hi> to faith, and to all the truths which it reveales: nothing but the light of grace can work this <hi>pious affection</hi> in us. The light of Reaſon, although it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make all truths evident that are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, yet (as I ſaid before) there are many truths that may be diſcovered by it; namely,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:158509:23"/>ſuch as are of the law of nature; but then it cannot, like grace, work a <hi>pious affection</hi> in the ſoul towards them. The Divell ſees many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent truths by the naturall light of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: hee ſees that God is infinitely good, and infinitely wiſe, and infinitely juſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely mercifull, and infinitely happy; but hee can have no <hi>affection</hi> to theſe truths: hee ſees them all <hi>in lumine coacto,</hi> in a forced and compelled light; and not <hi>in lumine jucundo,</hi> in a delightfull and pleaſant light. A theefe may know by the light of reaſon, that theft is an unjuſt act, or an adulterer that adultery is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull; but they can have no <hi>affection</hi> to theſe truths: their faith is like the Divels, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them by the force and compulſion of Reaſon, and not with delight and pleaſure. But the light of grace doth not onely make truth evident, but it produceth alſo in the ſoul a <hi>pious affection</hi> towards that truth; it makes a man to be in love with it, and to delight in it: <hi>I have had as great delight in the way of thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, as in all manner of riches,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.14. And ſo ſay all they whoſe <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings</hi> are enlightned by grace. He that hath the light of reaſon, can delight onely in ſuch
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:158509:24"/>truths as entertain and ſecond his humour: but hee that hath the light of grace, delights e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually in all truths, though they ſeem directly to oppoſe his profit, honour, pleaſure, and all his other deſires. Hee that hath this ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall gift, can ſay, like <hi>David,</hi> of all divine truths; <hi>More to be deſired are they then gold, yea then much fine gold; ſweeter alſo then the honey and the honey-comb, Pſal.</hi> 19.10. Whoſoever then finds in himſelfe this <hi>pious affection</hi> to faith, and to all the truths that it reveales, may aſſure himſelfe, his <hi>vnderstanding</hi> is enlightened by grace: but hee that finds it not, whatſoever hee beleeves, his ſoule was never touched by the influence of this divine light. Men doe generally love ſuch things as they poſſeſſe themſelves; they which have faith cannot but love faith: it is our Saviour Chriſts manner of arguing with his diſciples; <hi>If yee were of the world, the world would love his own: but ye are not of the world, therefore the world hateth you, John</hi> 15.19. The ſumme and abſtract of our Saviours ſpeech is this; The world loves not a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all profeſsion, becauſe ſpirituall things are none of their owne; if ſpirituall things were their own, they would love a ſpirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:158509:24"/>So I may argue with others, If faith be their owne, they cannot but love faith, and the truths which it reveales. And this is the ſecond thing to which <hi>Davids</hi> petition muſt be applyed; namely, to the <hi>underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the third place this petition muſt be applyed to the <hi>will: Heal</hi> my <hi>will.</hi> For, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the wounds which the ſoule hath received, there are none greater or more mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall then thoſe that are in the <hi>will:</hi> the wound of Malice is worſe then either the wound of Infirmity, or of Ignorance; and therefore that muſt be <hi>healed</hi> before the ſoule can be in a ſafe condition. The <hi>will</hi> indeed is in a better caſe after the <hi>affections</hi> and <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> be <hi>healed,</hi> then it was before; for, being an indifferent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of it ſelfe, it is moved by the <hi>affections;</hi> and therefore when the <hi>affections</hi> are <hi>healed,</hi> it hath not ſuch ſtrong provocations to ſin: and being a blind faculty of it ſelf, it receives infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from the <hi>underſtanding;</hi> and therefore when the <hi>underſtanding</hi> is <hi>healed,</hi> it hath not ſuch falſe dictates to make it erre. Yet this is not ſufficient to <hi>heal</hi> the <hi>will:</hi> the <hi>will</hi> hath his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per wound, and ſo muſt have his proper cure. And here the manner of <hi>healing</hi> is ſtill by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:158509:25"/>grace: Grace hath heat for the <hi>will,</hi> as well as light for the <hi>underſtanding;</hi> otherwiſe it could not <hi>heal</hi> the ſoul ſufficiently: For the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell hath light, but he hath no heat: his name is <hi>Lucifer,</hi> which ſignifies a carrier of light; but it had been better for him (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>ſi ignifer magis eſſet quàm Lucifer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard de verb. Iſai. proph. ſerm. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> if hee had been a carrier of heat, rather then a carrier of light: light without heat doth him no good; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and not to love, doth but increaſe his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. But grace hath both light and heat; light, whereby it begets faith in the <hi>vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> and heat, wherby it begets love in the <hi>will:</hi> and this love is the chiefe of all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the beſt and moſt excellent effect of grace. I know there are ſome which give faith the precedency, whom I leave to enjoy their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: for my ſelfe, as in all other things, ſo for my part in ſpirituall graces, I ſubmit my will to Gods will, as knowing the leaſt is more then I am worthy of, yet my prayers ſhall alwayes be to have love in the exceſſe; which I will not onely deſire above all other ſpirituall graces, but above all them and all the joyes of heaven together: Faith is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon which wee muſt build our love;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:158509:25"/>(for how can wee love God as we ought, if wee beleeve not in him as wee ought?) and yet love may exceed faith in dignity, as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure may exceed the foundation in rich and coſtly materials. But I intend not to ſpeak of the excellency of love in generall; love hath many operations <hi>in via,</hi> whileſt we are in the way to heaven, beſides the <hi>healing</hi> of the <hi>will;</hi> and it hath many operations <hi>in patria,</hi> when wee are in heaven, where the <hi>will</hi> ſhall be perfectly <hi>healed:</hi> but all theſe are out of my Text, and ſhall be out of my diſcourſe. I will onely ſpeak of the operation that love hath in <hi>healing</hi> the <hi>will;</hi> and love, when it flowes from grace, hath an operation in this reſpect above all other things: for that alone is able to work true repentance in the <hi>will,</hi> to melt it with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin, to make it flexible, and to molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that ſtiffeneſſe and that hardneſſe that is in it. Yet, as Reaſon may work upon the <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> and upon the <hi>vnderstanding;</hi> ſo it may work alſo upon the <hi>will,</hi> but failes as much in <hi>healing</hi> this, as in <hi>healing</hi> the other faculties. There is a naturall repentance which ſprings from naturall reaſon; for hee that hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved many temporall bleſsings at the hands of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:158509:26"/>God, cannot chuſe (if hee followes the dictate of right reaſon) but love him; and if hee loves him, hee cannot but be grieved when hee ſins againſt him; for hee that loveth, will grieve for the leaſt offence committed againſt the thing beloved. Yet this ſorrow that ſprings from naturall reaſon is not ſufficient to <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>will:</hi> For firſt, it failes in the cauſe: A na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man may be ſorrowfull for his ſins, but hee hath not a fountain of ſorrow that flowes and ſtreames continually: that love that ſprings from naturall reaſon is ſoon extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and when the cauſe ceaſeth, ſorrow, that is the effect proceeding from it, muſt needs ceaſe. But that love that proceeds from grace is more durable, it is able to perpetuate ſorrow; hee that is endued with this love, hath a conſtant habit of repentance, and if at any time hee ſins through infirmity, his ſoule becomes immediately an houſe of mourning, an <hi>Hadad rimmon,</hi> a valley of lamentation. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It failes in the effect: That ſorrow that ſprings from naturall reaſon cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>will,</hi> and make it turn from ſin: a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man may be ſorrowfull for his ſinnes paſt, and have a full reſolution to abſtain from
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:158509:26"/>ſin for the time to come; but he cannot actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and performe his reſolutions; for reaſon may inable a man to make good reſolutions, but onely grace can inable him to keep them. Now when amendment of life is not joyned with ſorrow for ſinne, it rather makes new wounds then <hi>heales</hi> the old: <hi>Qui plangit pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; iterum committit peccatum, quaſi ſi quis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terem lavet crudum, quem quantò magis laverit, tantò magis lutum fecerit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore;</hi> hee that mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for his ſin, and yet ceaſeth not to commit ſin, is like him that waſheth a tile ſtone that is not well burnt, which is made more dirty by being often waſhed. Hee that is ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſinne, and reſolves to amend, begins well; but if his repentance end where it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, it is a ſigne his <hi>will</hi> is not yet <hi>healed.</hi> When good reſolutions vaniſh like the morning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, and are never put in execution, what fruit can they produce? but when reſolutions and actions, like the former and the later rain, ſucceed one another in their due ſeaſon, they cauſe a fruitfull increaſe of glory and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and it is an evident ſigne that the <hi>will</hi> is wrought upon by grace; for that love that ſprings from grace makes the ſoule affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:158509:27"/>to God, and carefull to abſtain from all ſuch actions as offend him: <hi>When Iſrael came out of Egypt, and the houſe of Jacob from among the ſtrange people, the ſea ſaw that and fled, Jordan was driven back, Pſal.</hi> 114.1, 3. The Iſraelites depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of Egypt to worſhip God in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, was a type of mans converſion to God by love; and the flight of the waters, was a type of the flight of ſin that follows upon it: <hi>Ante retrorſum aquae converſae fuerunt, nunc retror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum peccata converſa ſunt,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon that paſſage: there the waters, but here ſins are driven backward; there the courſe of the floud was ſtopped within its channell, but here the courſe of ſin is ſtopped in all the ſecret paſſages of the heart. And this is the third thing to which <hi>Davids</hi> petition muſt be applyed, namely, to his <hi>will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Davids</hi> ſoule is not yet perfectly <hi>healed,</hi> his <hi>conſcience</hi> was wounded too, and therefore in the laſt place this petition muſt be applied to his <hi>conſcience, Heal</hi> my <hi>conſcience.</hi> And here the manner of <hi>healing</hi> is ſomething different from the former: grace can <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>ſtaine</hi> of ſin, but it cannot <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>guilt;</hi> it can ſanctifie, but it cannot juſtifie the ſoule: nothing can
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:158509:27"/>take away the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin but forgiveneſſe of ſin; but ſin being forgiven, the obligation to puniſhment is taken away, then the <hi>conſcience</hi> is <hi>healed,</hi> and <hi>guilt</hi> is turned into innocence, fear into gladneſſe. In the 102. Pſalme <hi>David</hi> laments his own caſe very paſsionately; <hi>My dayes are conſumed away like ſmoak, and my bones are burnt up as it were a fire-brand: my heart is ſmitten downe and withered like graſſe, ſo that I forget to eat my bread. For the voice of my groaning my bones will ſcarce cleave to my fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. In the 103. Pſalme hee ſeems to rejoice as much, and breaks forth into elogies of praiſe: <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoul, and all that is within me praiſe his holy name. Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoul, and forget not all his benefits.</hi> What was it that tranſported him ſo ſuddenly from one paſsion to another? If you read the Pſalmes, you ſhall ſoon ſee the cauſe; his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> was wounded when hee made the 102. Pſalm, and <hi>healed</hi> when he made the 103. Pſalm; his ſins lay heavie upon his ſoule when hee made the one, and were forgiven him when hee made the other. As long as the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin diſquieted his <hi>conſcience,</hi> not all the glory of his Kingdome, nor the pomp of his Court, not all the delights of Canaan, though <hi>a land flowing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:158509:28"/>with milk and honey,</hi> could content his mind: but when his ſins were forgiven, hee found a ſudden alteration; that heavineſſe that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his heart vented it ſelfe, and gave place to joy: <hi>O Lord my God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I cryed unto thee, and thou hast healed me, Pſal.</hi> 30.2. And what enſued upon this? <hi>Thou hast turned</hi> (ſaith hee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) <hi>my heavineſſe into joy, thou hast put off my ſack cloth, and girded me with gladneſſe.</hi> That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of mind, that tranquillity of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that circle of joy wherewith his ſoul was girt, followed immediately upon the <hi>healing</hi> of his <hi>conſcience</hi> and forgiveneſſe of his ſins: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſin is as proper to <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin, as grace to <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>ſtaine:</hi> In the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to <hi>heal</hi> ſin, and to forgive ſin, are <hi>termini aequipollentes,</hi> termes which ſignifie the ſame things, and are promiſcuouſly taken the one for the other: <hi>Return, ye back-ſliding children, and I will heal your back-ſlidings, Jer.</hi> 3.22. Here you ſee, to heale their back-ſlidings, is to forgive their ſin. And ſo again; <hi>I have ſeen his ways, and will heale him; I will lead him alſo, and reſtore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts unto him, and to his mourners, Iſa.</hi> 57.18. <hi>I have ſeen his wayes, and will heale him:</hi> that is, I have ſeen his ſins, and will forgive them. But
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:158509:28"/>was not <hi>David healed</hi> before hee made this Pſalm? did not the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> tell him, <hi>The Lord alſo hath put away thy ſin,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13. He did: but <hi>David</hi> being aſſured by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, deſired yet a greater aſſurance: The rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Gods ſaints alwayes ſuſpect their owne poverty, and think that which they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in reſpect of that which they have not, and of that which they deſire to have: <hi>David</hi> was <hi>healed,</hi> the Lord had forgiven him all his ſins, and yet for all that hee deſires ſtill to be <hi>healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then learn, by <hi>Davids</hi> example, to be thus carefull and ſolicitous to have our ſoules <hi>healed. Pharaoh</hi> deſired to be delivered from the plagues of Egypt, but not from his hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart: Let us rather deſire the laſt, for the wounds of ſin are the worſt wounds. The Scripture hath in many places very artificially painted out the nature of ſin; but it alwayes borrowes colours from noxious and hurtfull creatures: it compares it to the baſilisk, to the viper, to the aſp, whoſe poyſonous qualities are deſtructive to the life of men: And it hath alſo in many places allegorically expreſſed the nature of ſin by many deadly diſeaſes; by the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:158509:29"/>leproſie, by the palſie, by the bloudy-flux, and ſometimes by death it ſelfe in the abſtract. By theſe, and many other expreſsions in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, yee may learn the nature of ſin, and ſee how dangerous her wounds are if they be not <hi>healed.</hi> Let us then doe as <hi>David</hi> did, let us ſeek unto the Lord, who is the Phyſician of our ſouls; hee onely is able by his grace to <hi>heale</hi> the <hi>ſtaine,</hi> and by his mercy the <hi>guilt</hi> of our ſins.</p>
            <p>The time will not permit mee to enter into the laſt part of my Text, I will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with that of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah; Heal us, O Lord, and we ſhall be healed: ſave us, and we ſhall be ſaved; for thou art our praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:158509:29"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM 41.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Heal my ſoul, for I have ſinned againſt thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have formerly begun to ſpeak of theſe words in this place. I divided my Text then (as you may remember) into three parts; Firſt, here is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignatio partis vulneratae, Davids</hi> diſcovery of the wounded part; and that was his <hi>ſoul:</hi> Heal my <hi>ſoul.</hi> Secondly, here is <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio remedii,</hi> his prayer and petition for a remedy; and that was, to be <hi>healed: Heal</hi> my ſoul. Thirdly, here is <hi>Confeſsio cauſae,</hi> his confeſsion of the cauſe of thoſe wounds; and that was <hi>ſin:</hi> for I have <hi>ſinned</hi> againſt thee. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken of the two firſt parts; where I ſhewed you the wounds of his ſoule, and the manner how they were to be healed. I come now to ſpeak of the laſt part, which is, His
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:158509:30"/>confeſsion of the cauſe of thoſe wounds, in theſe words, <hi>For I have ſinned against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The right method of healing requires that wee ſhew the cauſe of the malady, as far as we are able; for, the cauſe being removed, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect will ceaſe: that <hi>David</hi> doth here in theſe laſt words, <hi>For I have ſinned againſt thee.</hi> And this laſt part of my Text is that which we are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to look upon, and to take into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For before (as I have ſhewed you) hee gave occaſion to thoſe that were of the Church, to ſin; to thoſe that were out of it, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme: firſt, he commits adultery; and after that, as if adultery were to be purged by mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or as if <hi>Uriah's</hi> loſt honour had been to be repaired by the loſſe of his life, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him to be unjuſtly murthered: But here you may ſee him marking out the way to repentance, and going himſelfe before to direct us. For, as hee was not aſhamed to commit ſin, ſo hee was not aſhamed to <hi>confeſſe</hi> it, and to make publick ſatisfaction to the whole world; for my Text, and many other places of the Pſalmes, remaine as it were ſo many publick regiſters of his ſins; hee ſighed, and wept, and lamented day and night, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:158509:30"/>(in a word) ſhewed all the marks and tokens of an humble and contrite heart, broken with the ſenſe of his ſins, and the apprehenſion of Gods anger againſt them. If a gold ring be broken, it loſeth part of its grace and luſtre; but if ye ſet a diamond, or a ſaphyr, or a ruby in the broken place, it gives a greater luſtre then it did before: ſo <hi>David,</hi> by his ſins, loſt part of that grace and luſtre that made him ſhine ſo brightly in the Church of God; but his <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, humility, repentance,</hi> and other <hi>vertues</hi> (like ſo many precious ſtones ſet in a gold ring in the place where it was broken) hath made him ſhine brighter after his fall, then in his former times of innocence; for, as his ſinnes were great, ſo was his ſorrow and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and I would to God that all men which have eyes to ſee the one, had eyes alſo to ſee the other; and could learn, not to love that in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> hated in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>This generall <hi>confeſsion</hi> containeth in it three particular <hi>confeſsions,</hi> which are the heads I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at this time, by Gods help, to inſiſt upon. Firſt, here is a <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>ſubject.</hi> Secondly, here is a <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>act.</hi> Thirdly, here is a <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:158509:31"/>the <hi>object.</hi> The <hi>ſubject, I.</hi> The <hi>act, Have ſinned.</hi> The <hi>object, Against thee.</hi> I will begin with the firſt; that is, his <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have ſinned:</hi> that is, <hi>I</hi> alone; not as a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and leſſe principall cauſe, neceſsitated and compelled by a cauſe more active and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then my ſelfe; but by the free and full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of my will: <hi>I</hi> have ſo ſinned, that theſe ſins are properly and onely <hi>mine.</hi> It is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of many to excuſe themſelves, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their ſins to others; or at leaſt, they will charge others to have had ſuch a cauſality and influence upon them, that they will ſeeme themſelves to be but partiall cauſes at the moſt. In <hi>Solomons</hi> time two mothers contended for one child, and both of them challenged it to be their owne; but when ſinne is borne and brought into the world, the contention is, who ſhall not have it: in this caſe the true mother would have the child divided; as in that, the falſe: the Will, whoſe child it is, will not acknowledge it for her owne; and when ſhee cannot wholly impoſe it upon others, ſhee deſires at leaſt to have it divided between them.</p>
            <p>Some impute their ſins to the <hi>Devill,</hi> and to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:158509:31"/>the violence of his temptations, as if hee did forcibly and irreſiſtibly procure them to ſin: and this is a kind of hereditary diſeaſe, which we take from our firſt parents; for after <hi>Eve</hi> had tranſgreſſed the commandement of God by eating the forbidden fruit, to excuſe the matter, ſhee laid the fault upon the <hi>Divell, The Serpent</hi> (ſaid ſhee) <hi>beguiled me, and I did eat.</hi> But <hi>David</hi> here uſeth no ſuch evaſions; <hi>I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> ſaith hee: hee condemnes himſelfe, and not the <hi>Divell;</hi> and yet the <hi>Divell</hi> ſinned as well as <hi>David:</hi> and, if Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> opinion be true, the <hi>Divell</hi> ſinned worſe then <hi>David;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de libero arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio, cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gravius eſt peccatum alteri per invidentiam dolúmque ſuadere, quàm ad peccandum alterius ſuaſione tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci,</hi> ſaith hee, ſpeaking of the temptations of the <hi>Divell.</hi> But yet <hi>David</hi> accuſeth not the <hi>Divell,</hi> who did only tempt, but could not conſtrain him to ſin; for all that the <hi>Divell</hi> can doe, is to allure and induce men by morall perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee cannot phyſically determine their wils to evill; hee may <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>6.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>91.</hi>
               </note> (as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks) ſupplant, cozen, and deceive a man, but he cannot force him to doe evill. When the <hi>Divell</hi> tempted our Saviour Chriſt in the wilderneſſe, without queſtion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:158509:32"/>hee imployed all the power hee had to make him ſin; and yet hee could not force him to it, nay, hee did not ſo much as offer to make him ſin by force; for, if yee conſider all the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges between them, yee ſhall find great Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, great Pride, and great Malice in his temptations, but no force at all: his firſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (as they are writ in order by Saint <hi>Luke</hi>) was this,<note place="margin">Luke 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>If thou be the Son of God, command this ſtone that it be made bread:</hi> Here is great bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this temptation; What, will nothing but a miracle ſerve the turne? Muſt Chriſt turn ſtones into bread to ſatisfie his curioſity? This was a bold requeſt indeed; but yet you ſee hee doth not force his conſent, but beg it. The ſecond temptation (after hee had ſet him upon a mountaine, and ſhowne him all the kingdomes of the world) was this; <hi>All this power will I give thee, and the glory of them; for that is delivered unto me, and to whomſoever I will, I give it: if thou therefore wilt worſhip mee, all ſhall be thine.</hi> Here is great pride in this temptation, a pride greater then that that made him fall from heaven; for then hee ſaid, <hi>Aſcendam ſuper excelſa nubis, ſimilis ero Altiſsimo: I will aſcend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the higheſt of the clouds, I will be like the moſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:158509:32"/>High, Iſa.</hi> 14.14. but here his pride reacheth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree higher, hee deſires to be greater then God, and requires of him, that hee would fall down and worſhip him; but yet you ſee here is no force in this temptation, <hi>If thou wilt worſhip mee</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>all ſhall be thine:</hi> hee leaves him here to his own free choice, if hee will, hee may; if hee will not, hee offers not by any violent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault to make him. His third temptation (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had ſet him upon the pinnacle of the Temple) was this; <hi>If thou be the Son of God, cast thy ſelfe down from hence.</hi> Here is great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in this temptation; for if hee would have caſt himſelfe down, the <hi>Divell</hi> thought that in all probability hee ſhould periſh by the fall: but yet you ſee no force in this temptation; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadere poteſt, praecipitare non poteſt</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Jerome</hi> upon this paſſage,) the <hi>Divell</hi> might perſwade him to throw himſelfe head-long, but could not throw him head-long by force: and this is all that the <hi>Divell</hi> can doe; if wee will not caſt our ſelves head-long, the <hi>Divell</hi> cannot. For ſins are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> calls them) they are plants ſet by the Will, and are not planted by the <hi>Divell</hi> in the ſoile where they grow. For God hath not onely given a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:158509:33"/>man the government of the world, but alſo the government of himſelfe, and hath made him ſo independent in reſpect of all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that if all the powers of hell ſhould ſet themſelves in oppoſition againſt one ſingle man, they could not force his Will: the Will, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> cannot be bound either with ropes or withs; her liberty ſits on her like a coat of male, and like the ſcales of the Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, it is impoſsible to offend her or hurt her by force. It is true, I confeſſe, that humane nature is corrupted and depraved, and cannot, without the help of ſupernaturall grace, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme a good action: it cannot work out of faith or love, which are neceſſary qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required in all that wee doe; but yet it is free in evill, it is flexible to this or that object, and can doe or not doe any naturall action, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the outward ſubſtance and matter of it. No man is bound to follow the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of the <hi>Divell,</hi> but may follow the dictate of his own reaſon; all that the <hi>Divell</hi> can doe, is, by applying his temptations, to move the Will to this or that object; hee cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine or fix her upon it: the Will indeed doth uſually goe as it is moved by outward objects,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:158509:33"/>being wonne with the charmes and delights which it hopes to find in them; but yet her election is free in this caſe, and not wreſted from her by force. There is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men and beaſts: beaſts are carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the outward bravery of every ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that preſents it ſelfe unto them, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refuſe their appetite thoſe things which it requireth: but men are moved by inward rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as well as by outward objects, and may, by the help of the one, beat back the impulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the other. Wee muſt not therefore make the <hi>Divell</hi> the authour of our ſins, for his temptations doe onely move, but cannot determine the Will to this or that evill: The <hi>Divell</hi> is a ſuiter to the Will, and not her ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher; <hi>Non enim cogendo, ſed ſuadendo nocet, nec ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torquet à nobis conſenſum, ſed petit,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine:</hi> the <hi>Divell</hi> hurts us by perſwaſion, not by conſtraint; and when wee commit a ſin, hee doth not raviſh our conſent, but ſues for it. No man is driven by the <hi>Divell</hi> to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate courſes, but goes willingly and of his owne accord; the <hi>Divell</hi> drives no man, but makes uſe onely of our owne corruption to perſwade us.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:158509:34"/>
            <p>Secondly, there are ſome that impute their ſins to <hi>deſtiny;</hi> that is, to a neceſſary concatena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſecond cauſes, which are ſo ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate one to another, that all things happen by neceſsity; inferiour cauſes, and amongſt them the wils of men, being carried and moved ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtibly by their ſuperiour: and this force of moving mens wils irreſiſtibly they attribute chiefly to the <hi>planets,</hi> and to ſeverall <hi>conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the heavens; as if men were neceſsitated to evill by their malignant influences, or as if the <hi>ſtarres</hi> ruled over mens wils (as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> over the Syracuſians) by an arbitrary and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall kind of government. Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his Commentaries upon the 31. Pſalme, makes mention of ſome that were of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which did undertake to fore-tell the ſins that any man ſhould fall into, by looking upon the <hi>ſtarres</hi> that ruled at his nativity; <hi>Et dicunt, quis quando vel peccet, vel bene vivat, &amp; quando</hi> Mars <hi>faciat homicidam, &amp;</hi> Venus <hi>adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> they took upon them to declare who ſhould be good or bad, when <hi>Mars</hi> ſhould force a man to commit murther, or <hi>Venus</hi> to commit adultery. But <hi>David</hi> here accuſeth not the <hi>ſtarres;</hi> hee clears them, and condemns
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:158509:34"/>himſelfe. <hi>Uriah</hi> might have growne gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed in the chaſte imbraces of his wife; hee might have long enough enjoyed his breath, and ſhee her honour, had <hi>David</hi> done no more but what the influence of the <hi>heavens</hi> compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to; for the <hi>heavens</hi> force no man to ſin: Had they the conduct of our wils, there would not be ſo many ſins committed as there are; they would govern us better then wee doe our ſelves. When our Saviour Chriſt was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the <hi>ſunne</hi> and the <hi>ſtarres</hi> withdrew their light, and were aſhamed to looke upon the cruelty and ingratitude that was committed by men. Can wee think then the <hi>ſtarres</hi> were the authors of thoſe evils which they bluſhed to behold? Can deeds of darkneſſe ſpring from the fountains of light? Without doubt, the <hi>ſtars</hi> are ſo farre from conſtraining any to ſin againſt God, that they would ſooner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their vertue from the world, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a ſinner either light or influence, had not God commanded them to ſhine upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, as well as upon the juſt. Let no man then accuſe the <hi>ſtarres,</hi> for their influence is not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but good; they are the cauſe of all action and motion, the ſpring of joy and delight; they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:158509:35"/>ſhed abroad their vertue through all inferiour bodies, and adde ſtrength and vigour to all things living; and if at any time they ſtirre up our inclinations to any exceſſe or defect, yet they offer no violence to the Will, but leave her in poſſeſsion of her full liberty: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if the Will were neceſsitated by the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> it were in vaine to conſult, in vaine to ſearch reaſons and motives for thoſe acts whereunto wee are violently carryed by <hi>desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> In this conſtraint, as there ſhould be no place left for liberty; ſo there could be none for vertue or vice: all puniſhments, how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall ſoever in outward appearance, yet in ſubſtance and truth ſhould be unjuſt, ſeeing they could not reach the principall authour of any ſin. What can be more unjuſt, then that a man ſhould beare the puniſhments of thoſe ſins which are committed by the <hi>heavens?</hi> If the <hi>ſtars</hi> be the principall cauſe of ſin, the <hi>ſtars</hi> ſhould beare the puniſhment; <hi>heaven</hi> ſhould go to hell, and men, which are but ſubordinate inſtruments, whoſe wils are over-ruled and over-topt by thoſe ſuperiour powers, ſhould be diſmiſſed and freed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there be ſome that impute their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:158509:35"/>ſins to <hi>God:</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (in the place before quoted) makes mention of thoſe too; affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that there were divers that gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves free ſcope and liberty to ſin, and then ſaid, they committed thoſe ſins, <hi>quia Deus ſic voluit,</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> would have it ſo; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>God</hi> the firſt mover and principall actor, and themſelves onely his under agents in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and this indeed hath alwayes been a common cuſtome, as <hi>Solomon</hi> (long before St. <hi>Augustines</hi> time) complained; <hi>The fooliſhneſſe of man</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>perverteth his way, and his ſoul fretteth against the Lord, Prov.</hi> 19.3. But <hi>David</hi> here accuſeth not <hi>God,</hi> hee clears him as well as others; and indeed, it had been the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable and unjuſt excuſe that he could have invented: for, doe but look upon the world, and yee ſhall ſee it the ſumme of perfection; it is as a table whereon the divine Wiſdome hath expreſſed many rich inventions, and diſplayed them all in ſuch colours, as it is impoſsible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſhould be more compleat, abſolute, and perfect: if there be any diſorders, or any thing imperfect in it, they are the effects of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes, and were not made ſo by <hi>God;</hi> and if no diſorder or no imperfect thing can
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:158509:36"/>come from <hi>God;</hi> then ſurely no ſin, which is nothing elſe but diſorder and imperfection. Let no man then pin his ſinnes upon <hi>God,</hi> or thinke within himſelfe, that <hi>God</hi> conſtrained him to ſin; <hi>Say not thou, It is through the Lord that I fell away: for thou oughteſt not to doe that which hee hateth. Say not thou, Hee hath cauſed me to erre: for hee hath no need of the ſinfull man, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus</hi> 15.11, 12. <hi>God</hi> created not the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee wanted a place to be in; neither did he create men, becauſe hee wanted ſome to ſet forth his goodneſſe by their praiſes, and others to under-prop his glory by their ſins: for <hi>God</hi> was in himſelfe before hee created the world, and was both the Theater and the Judge of his owne action; his owne applauſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of himſelfe was ſufficient to his own happineſſe, though men had never been created. <hi>God</hi> was as happy before hee made the world, as hee hath been ſince; and ſhould be as happy if it were turned into nothing, as hee is. Let no man therefore think, that <hi>God</hi> hath need of the ſinner, or that it is hee which procures his fall; for whoſoever ſinneth, puls down ruine upon himſelfe; hee is not <hi>Gods</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, but the principall cauſe of his owne
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:158509:36"/>wickedneſſe: <hi>Loe, this onely have I found,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>that God hath made man upright; but they have ſought out many inventions, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> therefore here layes all the fault upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee cleares <hi>God,</hi> nay, hee cleares all the world: <hi>I</hi> have ſinned; not <hi>God,</hi> nor the <hi>ſtars,</hi> nor the <hi>Divell,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> alone: It is onely <hi>I</hi> that have ſinned.</p>
            <p>And this is the firſt part of <hi>Davids confeſsion,</hi> wherein hee <hi>confeſſeth</hi> his ſin to be his owne: and thus muſt wee doe too. The firſt thing that wee are to <hi>confeſſe,</hi> is, that our ſins are our own; wee muſt not ſeek to another authour for them, nor aſcribe them to any predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant cauſe: if our ſouls be wounded as <hi>Davids</hi> was, the fault is our own. Other things may hurt our <hi>bodies,</hi> but they cannot hurt our <hi>ſouls;</hi> the <hi>ſoule</hi> hath an immunity and priviledge in this reſpect above the <hi>body,</hi> nothing can hurt it but it ſelfe: <hi>Therefore now thus ſaith the Lord, the God of hoſts, the God of Iſrael, Wherefore commit you this great evill against your ſoules, to cut off from you man and woman, child and ſuckling out of Judah, to leave you none to remain? Jer.</hi> 44.7. <hi>Wherefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you this great evill againſt your ſouls?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet condemns them here (you ſee) as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:158509:37"/>cauſes of their owne ruine, they were the contrivers of their own deſtruction, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted evill againſt their own ſouls, and were not ſubſervient inſtruments to another. Let us not then ſtrive to excuſe our ſins: our ſins are our owne, committed willingly and freely by us; and therefore wee muſt not blame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but our ſelves. Yea, our ſins are ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our own, that there is nothing in the world ſo much our owne as they: for, in reſpect of all other things wee are ſtewards, not owners; the diſpenſation is ours, but not the propriety: but our ſins are truly ours, we are the owners and proprietaries of them. Other things are none of ours; wee our ſelves are not our own, our bodies and ſoules are none of ours,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19, 20.</note> but Gods, and hee may diſpoſe of them as hee pleaſes: and when our bodies, or ſouls, or any thing that wee poſſeſſe are called our owne, it is not in reſpect of an abſolute and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but in reſpect of a limited and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent right which we hold under him; for we gave not our ſelves a being, but received it of God; yea, we were ſo farre from giving our ſelves a being when wee were not, that wee cannot continue our being now wee have it:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:158509:37"/>the world hath no leſſe need of his aſsiſtance now, then at the firſt creation; and when it ſhall have laſted ten thouſand yeers, it ſhall be ſtill in its minority; it muſt be no leſſe ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God when it is old, then in its firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy. And, as wee our ſelves are not our owne, but Gods; ſo our actions are none of ours, but his: he co-operates with all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and gives them vertue and ſtrength to performe their actions. Had they not a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſupply and contribution of power and ſtrength from him, the ſtarres would loſe their light, the heavens their influence, all things would become naked, diſarmed, and ſtript of all their qualities; all the old elements would be diſſolved, and in ſtead of them darkneſſe, ſilence, horror, and confuſion would be the new elements of the world. Wee cannot ſo much as eat, or drink, or move, or ſpeak with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; <hi>for in him wee live, and move, and have our being, Acts</hi> 17.28. not onely our being, but our life and motion; that is, all our actions are from him. Now, if we be neither owners of our ſelves, nor of our actions, then ſurely thoſe things which are without us, as riches, honours, and whatſoever elſe is in the world,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:158509:38"/>is none of ours, wee cannot call our ſelves the proprietaries of them: But for our ſins, they are truly our own, God hath no right at all in them; wee produce them, and give them a being of our ſelves, and therefore they are as truely ours, as any thing is his which hee crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But ſome perhaps will ſay, that God concurres as well to evill actions as to good; and therefore if our good actions muſt not be imputed to our ſelves, but to God; our evill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ought likewiſe to be imputed to him. To this I anſwer, that God concurreth to evill actions in ſuch a manner, as they cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuſtice be imputed to him. Its true, when a man ſins, God aſsiſts the ſinner, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curres with him in all ſubſervient actions that are requiſite to the ſin; yet the concourſe of God is ſo innocent, ſo pure, ſo void of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that no man can (without execrable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) call God the authour of that ſin. For there are two different things to be conſidered in every evill act; the firſt is the ſubſtance and matter of the act, and this (conſidered apart by it ſelfe) is neither morally good nor evill: The ſecond thing to be conſidered in every act is the obliquity and defect which accompanies
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:158509:38"/>it; that is, the diſorder which is in it, which makes it an evill act, and which doth as it were ſet a byas upon it, that drawes it awry: For the ſubſtance and matter of the act, God goes along with it, hee gives it the free contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of his help and concourſe; but for the obliquity and defect of the act, to that he doth not contribute at all; for it hath no efficient cauſe, but a deficient onely. When a lame man goes, there are two things in that act, his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his lameneſſe; his going proceeds from his ſoule, but his lameneſſe from ſome defect in the matter: And ſo it is in evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the actions themſelves proceed from God, as motion proceeds from the ſoule; but the obliquity of the actions proceeds from ſome defect in men, as lameneſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from ſome defect in the matter. So that Gods concourſe to our actions doth not (as you ſee) ſuppoſe his concourſe to the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and defect which is in them; the evill of every action is our own, though the action it ſelfe be Gods. And this is the firſt thing wee are to acknowledge when wee make our <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion;</hi> namely, that our ſins are our own, and that wee are not neceſsitated to commit them
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:158509:39"/>by any over-ruling power. And ſo much of the firſt part of <hi>Davids confeſsion,</hi> which is his <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>ſubject.</hi> I come now to the ſecond, which is his <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have ſinned: David</hi> proceeds here (you ſee) to <hi>confeſſe</hi> the <hi>act.</hi> Before hee <hi>confeſs'd</hi> the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of his hurt, and that was <hi>himſelfe:</hi> he goes forward now, and <hi>confeſſeth</hi> the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cauſe, and that was <hi>ſin;</hi> hee wounded himſelfe by <hi>ſin, For I have ſinned.</hi> And in this <hi>confeſsion</hi> hee layes open the nakedneſſe of his ſoule, without uſing vain excuſes to defend himſelfe: For although this <hi>confeſsion</hi> be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in generall terms, ſo that he ſeems not by it to acknowledge himſelfe ſo notorious and ſcandalous a ſinner as hee was: yet if yee read over the whole Pſalme, and conſider it well, you ſhall find, that this <hi>confeſsion</hi> muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of neceſsity to his worſt ſins; namely, to thoſe particular and individuall ſins of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery and Murther, and it is generally by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors chiefly applyed to them: For thoſe ſins which this <hi>confeſsion</hi> hath reference to, are thoſe which were publickly knowne, and which made him be evill ſpoken of amongſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:158509:39"/>his enemies, as wee may read in the reſt of the Pſalme; now thoſe were chiefly his Adultery and Murther: ſo that though they be not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in expreſſe termes, yet if yee conſider the reference my Text hath to other things contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Pſalme, there is enough expreſſed to make them known. And this muſt wee doe alſo in our <hi>confeſsion;</hi> it is not enough for us to <hi>confeſſe</hi> our ſins to be our owne, but wee muſt <hi>confeſſe</hi> the <hi>act</hi> alſo; wee muſt lay open, as far as we are able, every particular and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall ſin which wee commit. There are two wayes, as it hath been obſerved by ſome, to procure the favour of a Judge in civill Courts and Conſiſtories of juſtice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, either an open <hi>confeſsion,</hi> or elſe ſome <hi>colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable excuſe:</hi> but in Gods court there is but one of theſe wayes availeable; we may make him propitious and favourable by <hi>confeſsing</hi> our ſins, and relating all circumſtances that do aggravate them; but not by uſing <hi>colours</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate and leſſen them: they that deny or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their ſins, muſt look for no favour at the hand of God; <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>I will plead with thee, becauſe thou ſaiſt, I have not ſinned, Jer.</hi> 2.35. <hi>Behold, I will plead with thee;</hi> that is, I will
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:158509:40"/>alledge all that I can againſt thee, I will give thee the very extremity and rigour of juſtice, I will prove thee faulty, and convince thee to thy face. But on the other ſide, if men <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins, then is God ready to acquit and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them; <hi>If wee confeſſe our ſins, God is faithfull and just to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>confeſsion</hi> is either <hi>publick,</hi> or <hi>private: publick confeſsion</hi> is when the people at a publick congregation <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſinnes together; or, when ſome Miniſter of the Church <hi>confeſſeth</hi> in the name of all the people: and this may be either <hi>ordinary,</hi> or <hi>extraordinary; ordinary confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is at ordinary times, as upon Sabbath or feſtivall dayes, when the people meet together to <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſinnes: <hi>extraordinary confeſsion</hi> is when the people meet together at extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry times, upon ſpeciall emergent occaſions; and wee have divers examples in the Scripture of both theſe kinds of <hi>confeſsion,</hi> which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now ſtay to mention. <hi>Private confeſsion</hi> is when a private man <hi>confeſſeth</hi> his ſins; and it may be done <hi>publickly</hi> at a ſolemn aſſembly, or <hi>in private</hi> before a Miniſter of the Church, or to a <hi>friend,</hi> or before <hi>God.</hi> The firſt kind of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:158509:40"/>
               <hi>confeſsion</hi> was much in uſe in the primitive times of the Church; and it was performed many ſeverall wayes, which are frequently mentioned by the Fathers. The ſecond kind of <hi>confeſsion</hi> is exacted by the Church of Rome with great ſtrictneſſe and ſeverity, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon mens conſciences as a thing abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to ſalvation. The third kind of <hi>confeſsion</hi> hath been alwayes practiſed by good Chriſtians, as a thing conducing to the glory of God. The laſt kind of <hi>confeſsion</hi> is of abſolute neceſsity, and is generally exerciſed in the Church. As for our Church, wee allow all theſe kinds of <hi>confeſsion:</hi> for the firſt kind of <hi>confeſsion,</hi> which is to be made before a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick aſſembly, our Church in many caſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it, and enjoineth publick and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſinners (which cauſe the Church wherein they live to be evill ſpoken of) to do penance, to make an honourable amends, and to give a publick teſtimony of their ſorrow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for it. For the ſecond kind of <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> which is to be made privately before a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church, wee enjoine it not; but yet our Church in ſome caſes counſels it: as namely, when the conſcience is diſtreſſed and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:158509:41"/>perplexed, and cannot free it ſelfe from feares and doubts. For the third kind of <hi>confeſsion,</hi> that is to be made to a friend, it is approved alſo and commended by our Church, and is counſelled by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>James,</hi> who admoniſheth the children of God to <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins one to another. For the laſt kind of <hi>confeſsion,</hi> (as I ſaid) it is of abſolute neceſsity, and is taught by our Church as a doctrine fundamentall, and neceſſary to ſalvation. Now if I ſhould ſpeak of all theſe kinds of <hi>confeſsions,</hi> firſt, of <hi>publick confeſsion,</hi> both <hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary;</hi> and then of <hi>private confeſsion,</hi> and all the ſeverall kinds of it; if I ſhould ſpeak of the manner how they are to be performed, and of the profit and benefit that is in them, I ſhould too much exceed the limits of the time: I will ſpeak therefore onely of the laſt kind, that is, <hi>confeſsion before God;</hi> becauſe that is neceſſary to ſalvation, and is a duty that cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed with. Whoſoever looks to have his ſoule healed, muſt firſt <hi>confeſſe</hi> his ſin to God, and lay open the cauſe of his diſtemper. And ſurely wee cannot deſire a more cheap, or a more eaſie remedy: wee ſhall not need to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent our ſpirituall diſeaſes in plates of gold,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:158509:41"/>as the Philiſtines did their <hi>emerods;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.4.</note> that was a coſtly remedy, and yet they thought it cheap enough, when they conſidered what an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe it was to have their health. But wee ſhall not need (I ſay) to uſe ſuch a coſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, wee ſhall not need to repreſent our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall diſeaſes in plates of gold; let us but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them in words, and wee ſhall be heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>David</hi> did but <hi>confeſſe</hi> his ſin, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained pardon; the prodigall child did but <hi>confeſſe</hi> his ſin, and preſently the cloud of his fathers anger was diſſolved into a milde ſhowre of teares; the theefe upon the croſſe, <hi>confeſsing</hi> his ſins, was canonized before hee was dead, and found a better paradiſe by <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> then <hi>Adam</hi> loſt by ſin: Let us then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſins, and wee ſhall have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; let us lay open and diſcover the cauſe of our wounds, and wee ſhall be healed.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps will ſay, All this is done already; I have and doe <hi>confeſſe</hi> my ſins before God every day. It is well done: yet take heed thou doſt not content thy ſelfe with the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>confeſsion.</hi> What if thy <hi>confeſsion</hi> be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an empty ſound of words? What if it want ſubſtance? What if it be but a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:158509:42"/>meer formality? then thou art miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded: Yet ſuch is the <hi>confeſsion</hi> of moſt men; for there is a formall verball <hi>confeſsion,</hi> which is but a meer ſhadow; a man may <hi>confeſſe</hi> his ſins every day, and yet be never the better, for there are divers conditions neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsion,</hi> which, if they be abſent from thine, it will not be available.</p>
            <p>The firſt condition neceſſary to a true <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> is <hi>a due examination of our ſelves, and of our former life;</hi> all the kinds of ſin, and all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that doe aggravate them, are to be diſcuſſed: wee are not to take our ſins in the groſſe, and ſo to make a light perfunctory <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> and ſay, that wee are miſerable and wretched ſinners; but wee muſt take a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect view (as far as we are able) of all our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and individuall ſins. It is for want of this <hi>examination</hi> that many a mans <hi>confeſsion</hi> is inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid; they <hi>confeſſe</hi> only ſuch ſins as come ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into their minds, and make no reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their former life. But whoſoever deſire to make ſuch a <hi>confeſsion</hi> as may be pleaſing to God, muſt take more paines, and do it more exactly; <hi>Stand in awe and ſin not, commune with your own heart, and in your chamber, and be ſtill,</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:158509:42"/>
               <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. As if hee ſhould have ſaid, In the ſilence of the night, when thou enjoyeſt thine owne privacie, when thou art free from the cares and diſtractions of worldly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, enter into ſecret communication with thine owne heart, <hi>examine</hi> thine owne wayes, and ſearch out thine own corruptions. And, leſt hee ſhould ſeeme to exact that of others, which hee did not perform as rigorouſly him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee ſhewes it in another Pſalme to be his owne practice; <hi>I call to remembrance</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>my ſong in the night, I commune with mine owne heart, and my ſpirit made diligent ſearch, Pſal.</hi> 77.6. The Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> likewiſe exhorts his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Jewes, in the time of their captivity, to the performance of this duty; <hi>Let us ſearch and try our wayes</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>and turn again to the Lord, Lam.</hi> 3.40. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo (writing to the Corinthians) layes this as a neceſſary injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon them, that no man ſhould have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to the holy Sacrament, without diligent <hi>examination</hi> of himſelfe; <hi>But let a man examine himſelfe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. As if he ſhould have ſaid, It is not ſufficient to make a generall <hi>confeſsion</hi> of your ſinnes when yee receive the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:158509:43"/>holy Sacrament; but every man muſt ſearch accurately, that, if it be poſsible, hee may ſee the very bottome of his corruption, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe</hi> all his ſins, and be humbled for them in that meaſure that their number or quality doe require. It is for want of this <hi>examination,</hi> that many men think themſelves better then they are, they take no notice of their ſins; or, if they doe take notice when they commit them, yet, for want of a timely <hi>examination,</hi> they forget them afterwards: ſo that when they would <hi>confeſſe,</hi> their ſins (like <hi>Nebuchad-nezzars</hi> dream) are quite gone out of their mind; and if ſome <hi>Daniel</hi> doe not bring them back again to their remembrance, they ſhall never be <hi>confeſſed.</hi> But this ſlight and ſuperficiall kind of <hi>confeſsion</hi> is not availeable; they that would <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins effectually, muſt be intentive and diligent in <hi>examination</hi> of themſelves, that ſo they may diſcover the whole maſſe of their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: and as divers artificers <hi>examine</hi> all their work by the line and plummet, ſo they muſt <hi>examine</hi> all their actions by the exact rule and ſtraight line of Gods word. And here (would the time permit) I would a little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my ſelfe, becauſe there are many that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:158509:43"/>yet performed this duty; and many others that know not how to do it: there are many that never yet performed this duty, which are ſo farre from taking any <hi>ſtrict account</hi> of their owne wayes, and from <hi>ſearching diligently</hi> into their owne lives, that ſo they might diſcover their own imperfections, and judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them in themſelves, that they are not very well content when others would take the paines to doe it for them, and to lay open their ſins and corruptions before their eyes; but if their paſtor or teacher (whoſe office it is to doe it, and who ſhall anſwer God for not doing it) take notice of any ſin, and diſcover it to them, they think him too uncivill and importunate. If there be any here that have been thus negligent in <hi>confeſsing</hi> their ſins, and <hi>examining</hi> their owne lives, be exhorted, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, to begin this duty before your ſouls be too far over-ſpread with ſins: <hi>I went by the field of the ſlothfull</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>and by the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the man void of understanding, and loe, it was all growne over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the ſtone-wall thereof was broken down, Pro.</hi> 24.30, 31. His words are allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and imply thus much, that they which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:158509:44"/>neglect this duty, and doe not ſeriouſly <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and often <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins, their ſoules will ſoon be over-growne with vices, as the field or vine-yard of a fool or ſlothfull perſon uſeth to be over-grown with weeds. There are ſome again that know not how to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this duty, which are ſubject to deceive themſelves, to let many ſins paſſe undiſcerned, and oftentimes to miſtake them for vertues. If there be any ſuch here, (as I am afraid there are too many) let mee deſire you to obſerve theſe two rules for your direction: Firſt, when yee <hi>examine</hi> your actions, take heed you weigh them not by a falſe balance; that is, by a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſcience, for a defiled conſcience is as a falſe balance; it is impoſsible to weigh an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction rightly by it. The Jewes having a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſcience, preferred <hi>Barabbas</hi> before our Saviour Chriſt. And this is that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives many, when they <hi>examine</hi> themſelves, and find they doe nothing againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they think themſelves very upright and juſt; but they know not that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is defiled, they conſider not that their affection ſwayes their conſcience, and can make it judge any thing lawfull or unlawfull,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:158509:44"/>as it pleaſe. But you will ſay, How ſhall I know when my conſcience is defiled? The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will reſolve that doubt; <hi>Unto the pure</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>all things are pure; but unto them that are defiled and unbeleeving nothing is pure, but even their mind and conſcience is defiled, Titus</hi> 1.15. Whoſoever therefore lives in any habituall ſin; whoſoever alloweth himſelfe to doe wickedly in any thing, his conſcience is defiled, and it is in vain for him to conſult with it concerning the lawfulneſſe or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of any action. Secondly, when you <hi>examine</hi> your actions, favour not your ſelves, but give the ſame judgement upon your own ſins, and pronounce the ſame condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelves, which at other times ye have pronounced againſt others that have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the like offences. There are many, for want of obſerving this rule, which think themſelves to be much better then they are; they will cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſcoffe at others for thoſe ſins and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities which they commit every day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing them in themſelves. Would theſe men but look upon their owne actions with the ſame impartiall eye that they looke upon others, they would be able to judge better of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:158509:45"/>their owne wayes, and would diſcover the ſame corruptions in themſelves, which they can ſo eaſily diſcern in another. And this is the firſt condition neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsion;</hi> that is, a due <hi>examination</hi> of our ſelves, and of our former life.</p>
            <p>The ſecond condition neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsion,</hi> is, <hi>ſorrow and contrition of heart:</hi> They that <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins, and are not grieved for them, may be ſaid rather to relate or to deſcribe their ſins, then to <hi>confeſſe</hi> them. <hi>Sorrow</hi> is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſo inſeparable from this duty, that where it is wanting, it is as good to deny our ſins, as to <hi>confeſſe</hi> them: and this condition is expreſly required <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.40. where God makes a promiſe to the Jewes when they ſhall be in captivity, ſaying, <hi>If they ſhall confeſſe their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, with their treſpaſſe which they treſpaſſed against mee, and that they alſo have walked contrary unto mee; And that I alſo have walked contrary unto them, and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed hearts be humbled, and they then accept of the puniſhment of their iniquity: Then will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my covenant with Jacob, and alſo my covenant with Iſaac, and alſo my covenant with Abraham will I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:158509:45"/>remember, and I will remember the land.</hi> This promiſe (you ſee) which God made to the Jewes upon their <hi>confeſsion,</hi> is a conditionall promiſe, and the condition expreſſed is this, <hi>If their uncircumciſed hearts be humbled;</hi> that is, if they be broken and rent with <hi>ſorrow</hi> for their ſins: he doth not promiſe to remember them whenſoever they ſhould formally <hi>confeſſe,</hi> but if their uncircumciſed hearts were humbled when they made their <hi>confeſsion.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whereſoever you find the children of God <hi>confeſsing</hi> their ſins in Scripture, yee ſhall find them uſually in an humble and mournfull poſture: In ſuch a poſture ſhall you find <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> at the ninth chapter and third verſe of his own Prophecie; where you may ſee, that hee firſt humbled himſelfe, and, by putting on ſack-cloth and aſhes, expreſſed deep ſignes of <hi>ſorrow</hi> and <hi>contrition,</hi> and then hee proceeded to make <hi>confeſsion</hi> of his ſins. In ſuch a poſture ſhal ye find <hi>Ezra,</hi> at the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter and 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of his own book; where you may ſee, that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by the outward geſture of his body firſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the inward heavineſſe and affliction of his mind, and then proceeded to make his <hi>confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to God. And this is the true manner of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:158509:46"/>ſin; our <hi>confeſsion</hi> is then available, when our hearts are ready to break with <hi>ſorrow:</hi> wee may be confident the Lord will not deſpiſe us, when our <hi>tears</hi> lift up our <hi>confeſsion</hi> as the waters lifted up the Ark. I will not here diſpute the queſtion concerning the quality of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> whether a <hi>ſenſible ſorrow</hi> be alwaies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or whether an <hi>appreciative rationall ſorrow</hi> will ſerve the turn, as our Romiſh Doctors do generally affirme. For my part, I take their <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preciative rationall ſorrow</hi> to be a meer figment, a fained and forged invention of their owne, as many other of their diſtinctions are: <hi>Sorrow</hi> is a paſsion of the mind, and I think an apprecia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive rationall paſsion is a new kind of paſsion, that was never known to any but themſelves. True <hi>ſorrow,</hi> without doubt, hath alwayes ſome ſenſible motions, ſome convulſions of heart to attend it; it could not be a paſsion of the mind, if it did not <hi>inferre paſsionem animo,</hi> ſome wayes or other ſenſibly affect the ſoule. I will alſo omit the queſtion concerning the quantity of <hi>ſorrow</hi> which wee ought to have; namely, whether <hi>ſorrow</hi> for ſin ought to be the greateſt <hi>ſorrow. Bellarmines</hi> determination is, that it ought to be the greateſt <hi>appreciative,</hi> but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:158509:46"/>not <hi>intenſive.</hi> I will not at this time examine this determination; I ſay only in generall, that true <hi>ſorrow,</hi> proceeding from the grace of God, and not from the fear of puniſhment, or any other ſiniſter reſpect, in what degree or quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity ſoever it be, is ſufficient to make our <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> available before God. Many, when they compare their owne <hi>ſorrow</hi> with the <hi>ſorrow</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> or with the <hi>ſorrow</hi> of divers other holy men and women which are mentioned in the Scriptures, are much troubled in mind, becauſe they cannot equall them. What are my <hi>tears</hi> (ſay they) compared with <hi>Davids tears?</hi> What is my <hi>griefe,</hi> compared with the <hi>griefe</hi> of <hi>Mary Magdalen?</hi> Thus they diſcourſe within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and are ready almoſt to diſpaire, becauſe they cannot arrive at their perfection. But ſuch compariſons as theſe, beloved, are offenſive and unprofitable; for why ſhould every one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe with <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> which were Gods eſpeciall favourites, and had a greater meaſure of grace conferred upon them, then is ordinarily conferred upon others? Every one cannot hope to be ſo perfect as they were. I ſpeak not this to diſhearten any, or inclining to an opinion, that it is not lawfull
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:158509:47"/>for you to deſire to equall thoſe worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of repentance; for I think it not onely lawfull, but commendable for every one to deſire the beſt gifts: wee may deſire to equall, and (if wee can) to excell <hi>David, Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> or any other, provided alwayes, that wee ſubmit our wils to the will of God; and when wee ſee that it is not his pleaſure to conferre upon us ſuch gifts as he conferred upon them, wee muſt not therefore murmure againſt him, nor work our owne diſquiet and trouble by making ſuch unprofitable compariſons, but giving thanks to God for what wee have, let us comfort our ſelves with that; conſidering alwaies, that all <hi>ſorrow,</hi> whether it be in a great or ſmall quantity, if it proceeds from grace, is able to ſave our ſouls. And this is the ſecond condition neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsion;</hi> that is, <hi>ſorrow and true contrition of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third condition neceſſary to a true <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> is, <hi>amendment of life:</hi> Although a man <hi>confeſſeth</hi> his ſins every day, yet if hee forſakes them not, his <hi>confeſsion</hi> is but a meer formality; and this condition is required in many places of the Scripture; but I will onely name a place or two: In the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter of the <hi>Proverbs</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:158509:47"/>and the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, it is ſaid, <hi>Hee that covereth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper; but whoſo confeſſeth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh them ſhall have mercy.</hi> Not every hypocrite that makes a formall <hi>confeſsion,</hi> but he that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth</hi> and <hi>forſaketh</hi> his ſins ſhall have mercy. And again, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.11. <hi>Ezra</hi> ſaith unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Now therefore make confeſsion unto the Lord God of your fathers, and doe his pleaſure, and ſeparate your ſelves from the people of the land, and from the ſtrange wives.</hi> Hee doth not onely ſtirre up the people to <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſins to God, but to doe his pleaſure alſo, and to ſeparate themſelves from the people of the land with whom they had contracted affinity, and to put away their ſtrange wives, without which their <hi>confeſsion</hi> had been but vain. It is (I know) a common opinion at this time, that an <hi>actuall amendment</hi> of life is not neceſſary and eſſentiall to <hi>confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> but that a <hi>purpoſe of amendment,</hi> with <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> is ſufficient: and although they commit the ſame ſins every day, yet, if they reſolve to amend after they have committed them, many think themſelves (if they ſhould die after ſuch reſolutions) in a good and ſafe condition. But this, beloved, is a groſſe and manifeſt deluſion, and contrary to thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:158509:48"/>of Scripture that have been already alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to many other which might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to this purpoſe. It is true indeed, that <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> if it could be in any man without an <hi>actuall amendment,</hi> is able to ſave him: but herein they deceive themſelves, in that they think <hi>true faith</hi> conſiſtent with bare and naked reſolutions, and not alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with an <hi>actuall amendment;</hi> for <hi>true faith</hi> will ſhew it ſelfe in action, and cannot be perfected and known by bare and naked reſolutions: <hi>Whatſoever is born of God</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John</hi>) <hi>overcometh the world; and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4. By <hi>true faith</hi> therefore a man overcometh the world: now, how can hee be ſaid to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world, that hath not forſaken his ſins? for a victory is won by action, and not by bare and naked reſolutions. Have drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards (think you) overcome the world? Have adulterers, unclean perſons, ſwearers, and uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers overcome the world? No, they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come themſelves, and have not overcome the world. Take heed therefore yee deceive not your ſelves; think not yee have <hi>faith,</hi> before yee find the fruits of <hi>faith</hi> in your life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:158509:48"/>I preſume there are none here but will ſay they have <hi>faith;</hi> but I pray God many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you be not deluded. Should I demand of you, whether you beleeve in God, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye beleeve an heaven, and an hell, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead; I dare ſay, you would all anſwer, Yes: But then, if I could look into your lives, and ſee your ſecret practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I am afraid I ſhould find many of you to be ſuch, as if yet beleeved no ſuch matter. I ſay, If I could look into your lives, I am afraid I ſhould find many of you to be ſuch, as if yee beleeved neither heaven, not hell, nor the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, nor any other article of <hi>faith:</hi> for wherein doe many amongſt us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed an infidell, that beleeves none of theſe things? Is it poſsible that <hi>infidelity</hi> ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce as good effects in them, as <hi>faith</hi> in you? Is <hi>faith</hi> ſo ſluggiſh a vertue, that it can he ſtill, and not be active? No, be ſure, if thy <hi>faith</hi> breaks not into action, it is but a <hi>dead faith.</hi> In the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> there are many commended for <hi>faith;</hi> but they are all ſaid to have done ſomething by it: It is ſaid, <hi>By faith Abel offered a better ſacrifice then Cain;</hi> and ſo of all the reſt: it is ſaid, they did ſomething by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:158509:49"/>
               <hi>faith;</hi> but there are none which are ſaid to have made good reſolutions by <hi>faith,</hi> and to have kept none of them. <hi>True faith</hi> therefore muſt be known and perfected by action, and not by bare and naked reſolutions. And this is the third condition neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> that is, <hi>amendment of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth condition neceſſary to a true <hi>confeſsion,</hi> is, <hi>ſatisfaction.</hi> I ſhall not need to prove this condition neceſſarie, becauſe it is manifeſtly included in the former; for there can be no amendment without <hi>ſatisfaction:</hi> he that doth wrong another, and doth not repair the injury, cannot be ſaid to amend, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt juſtice; for juſtice giveth to every one his due, which he refuſeth to doe, that will not reſtore his neighbours goods, or his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours credit, when hee hath wrongfully depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him of them. Now therefore let every one examine his <hi>confeſsion,</hi> and ſee whether it hath all theſe conditions or no: Firſt, whether hee hath made a <hi>diligent examination</hi> of his whole life, and <hi>confeſſed</hi> all his particular and individuall ſins, as far as hee is able. Secondly, whether his <hi>confeſsion</hi> be joyned with <hi>true ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and contrition of heart.</hi> Thirdly, whether
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:158509:49"/>hee hath <hi>for ſaken</hi> the ſins which hee hath <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Fourthly, whether hee hath made <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (as far as hee is able) for all the wrongs and injuries he hath done: if his <hi>confeſsion</hi> hath all theſe conditions, it is good; but if it want any of them, hee hath but plaid the formall hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite. And ſo much of the ſecond part of <hi>Davids confeſsion,</hi> which is his <hi>confeſsion</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>act.</hi> I come now to the laſt part, which is, his <hi>confeſsion</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>object.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have ſinned againſt thee.</hi> The <hi>object</hi> againſt whom this ſin was committed is not expreſt in the words of my Text, but is implied in this word <hi>thee:</hi> yet wee ſhall not need to goe farre to ſeek it, for it is expreſſed in the ſame verſe; <hi>I ſaid, Lord, be mercifull unto mee; beale my ſoule, for I have ſinned against thee.</hi> It is the <hi>Lord God</hi> (you ſee) to whom this petition was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, hee it is to whom this <hi>thee</hi> hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: <hi>God</hi> then was the <hi>object</hi> againſt whom hee ſinned; and this is that wherein hee doth moſt of all ſet out his owne ungratefulneſſe: for if they that partake of the favours of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, cannot diſpence with their ſervice, if chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren owe great reſpects to their parents, ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to their maſter; then how could <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:158509:50"/>neglect this ſervice, withdraw this reſpect, and ſin againſt <hi>God,</hi> without committing (in one act) all the ingratitudes that can be committed. This is that which did moſt of all increaſe his guilt, and which (without queſtion) did moſt of all increaſe his ſorrow, who, like a zealous penitent, inflamed with divine love, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſin in many reſpects, was yet moſt of all enraged againſt it, becauſe it was committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God,</hi> who had obliged him to himſelf by many ſpeciall and extraordinary favours: for it was <hi>hee,</hi> that (like a father) brought him up of a little child, and which had many times (as it were) carried him in his armes; it was <hi>hee,</hi> that pulled the crowne from off the head of <hi>Saul,</hi> to ſet it upon his, and entailed it upon him and his poſterity for many generations; it was <hi>hee,</hi> that (like a maſter) inſtructed him in the law, and (like a King) protected him in all danger; and therefore, to ſin againſt <hi>him,</hi> was to ſtain his ſoul with the deepeſt colours of ingratitude.</p>
            <p>But why did <hi>David confeſſe</hi> onely that hee ſinned againſt <hi>God?</hi> Did he not ſin alſo againſt <hi>Uriah,</hi> who (by his ſecret practices) loſt his life? Did hee not ſin alſo againſt <hi>Bathſheba,</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:158509:50"/>who (by his ſubtle perſwaſions) loſt her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? Did he not ſin alſo againſt <hi>Joab,</hi> whom he had made confederate to his purpoſe? And did hee not ſinne alſo againſt the <hi>whole army,</hi> whoſe lives were all expoſed to the ſword of the children of <hi>Ammon?</hi> I anſwer, that hee ſinned againſt <hi>God,</hi> both in reſpect of himſelfe, and in reſpect of all theſe: for ſin is againſt <hi>God</hi> in a double reſpect, <hi>reſpectu ſui ipſius, &amp; reſpectu communitatis,</hi> as the School ſpeaks, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelfe, and in reſpect of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; that is, in reſpect of all the creatures. Firſt, ſin is againſt <hi>God reſpectu ſui ipſius,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelfe, for it is againſt his chiefeſt attributes; againſt his <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and againſt his <hi>juſtice,</hi> and againſt his <hi>mercy:</hi> firſt, it is againſt his <hi>wiſdome,</hi> for <hi>wiſdome</hi> enjoynes order; but ſin is alwayes accompanied with diſorder and confuſion: Secondly, it is againſt his <hi>juſtice,</hi> for <hi>juſtice</hi> commands that every one ſhould have his due; but ſin is alſo joyned with wrong and injury: Thirdly, it is againſt his <hi>mercy,</hi> for <hi>mercy</hi> deſires the preſervation of the world; but ſin tends to the ruine and deſtruction of it: to diſhonour our parents, to commit murther, or adultery, or to beare falſe witneſſe againſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:158509:51"/>our neighbours; what doe all theſe ſins, but tend to the ſubverſion of mankind? Men ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt by obſervation of the morall law, and would ſoon periſh without it: and therefore ſin, which tends to the ruine of mankind, is as much againſt Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> which wils their preſervation, as againſt any other of his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes; ſo that the malice of a ſinner is termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted immediately upon <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, hee is the <hi>object</hi> againſt whom ſin is committed, <hi>reſpectu ſui ipſius,</hi> in reſpect of himſelf. But that I may make this reaſon a little more cleare then the Schoole hath made it, I will lay downe this ground, That every ſinner wiſheth that it might be lawfull for him to commit thoſe ſins whereunto he is addicted, and that there were no eternall puniſhment prepared for them. This that I have laid for a ground, I think, will be eaſily granted; for all men deſire happineſſe: the Will, that is free in the means, is not free in the end; it cannot but deſire happineſſe, and abhorre all things that are deſtructive of it, and conſequently, cannot but abhorre an eternall puniſhment, which it knows to be incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible with happineſſe. Now then, if every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wiſheth that it might be lawfull for him
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:158509:51"/>to commit thoſe ſins whereunto hee is addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and that there were no eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments provided for them; what is this, but to wiſh that <hi>God</hi> were not ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> or ſo <hi>juſt,</hi> or ſo <hi>mercifull</hi> as he is, (for ſin, as I ſaid, is contrary to <hi>wiſdome, juſtice,</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi>) and conſequently, to wiſh that hee were not <hi>God;</hi> for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible hee ſhould be <hi>God,</hi> and not be infinitely wiſe, and infinitely juſt, and infinitely merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. They that would have <hi>God</hi> want thoſe perfections, would have him want his being, for his being is made up of thoſe perfections: ſo that all ſinners doe incluſively (though not expreſly) deſire <hi>Gods</hi> ruine, and that his very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and being were deſtroyed; for it is all one in ſubſtance, to deſire a thing directly, or by way of conſequence: As for example, he that deſires that it were night, doth in ſubſtance, and incluſively deſire the ſun were downe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he doth not expreſly and actually think upon the ſun. In like manner, they that deſire it might be lawfull for them to ſin, and that there were no eternall puniſhment appointed for ſinners, doe in ſubſtance and incluſively deſire, that <hi>God</hi> were not ſo wiſe, or ſo juſt, or ſo mercifull as hee is, although expreſly and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:158509:52"/>actually they do not think upon his wiſdome, or juſtice, or mercy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſin is againſt <hi>God, reſpectu communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> in reſpect of the community, or in reſpect of all the creatures; for the whole world is one community or incorporation, whereof <hi>God</hi> is the governour and protectour: the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are as it were the members, and hee is the head; and therefore whatſoever is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the community, or againſt the creatures, is done againſt <hi>God.</hi> Our Saviour <hi>Christ</hi> is the head and protector of the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever is done againſt the Church, is done againſt him: <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuted the Church, and our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> eſteemed that perſecution as an injury offered to himſelf; <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me? Act.</hi> 9.4. In the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall carriage of affaires in all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, that which is done againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth in generall, or againſt any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular member thereof, is done againſt the <hi>King:</hi> if one man kill another, the <hi>King</hi> will preſently be plaintiffe, and take the injury done unto himſelfe, becauſe the party ſlain was under his protection, and was a member of that body whereof he is the head: As <hi>Christ</hi> is in reſpect
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:158509:52"/>of the Church, and a <hi>King</hi> in reſpect of his kingdome; ſo is <hi>God</hi> in reſpect of the whole world: and therefore what injury ſoever is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to any of the creatures, is an injury to <hi>God;</hi> ſo that <hi>David</hi> ſinning againſt <hi>Uriah,</hi> and againſt <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and againſt <hi>Joab,</hi> and againſt the <hi>whole army,</hi> may be ſaid in that reſpect alſo to have ſinned againſt <hi>God.</hi> And thus you have ſeen all the parts of <hi>Davids confeſsion,</hi> both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>ſubject,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>act,</hi> and in reſpect of the <hi>object.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one God, be aſcribed all glory, and honour, and power, and wiſdome, now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
